<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <background>
    <name>Custom Background [2024]</name>
    <source book="Dungeon Master's Guide 2024" page="54"/>
    <description>
      <text>A character's background represents what the character did prior to becoming an adventurer. Creating a unique background or customizing an existing one from the Player's Handbook can reflect the particular theme of your campaign or elements of your world. You can also create a background to help a player craft the story they have in mind for their character.</text>
    </description>
    <ability_score_choice>
      <text>Choose three abilities that seem appropriate for the background:

Strength or Dexterity. These abilities are ideal for a background involving physical exertion.

Constitution. This ability is ideal for a background that involves endurance or long hours of activity.

Intelligence or Wisdom. One or both abilities are ideal for a background that focuses on cerebral or spiritual matters.

Charisma. This ability is ideal for a background that involves performance or social interaction.</text>
      <!-- Implicitly, the rule is to increase one by 2 and another by 1, or three by 1, as per PHB standard for backgrounds -->
    </ability_score_choice>
    <feat_choice>
      <text>Choose one feat from the Origin category. See the Player's Handbook for examples of Origin feats.</text>
      <category name="Origin"/>
    </feat_choice>
    <skill_proficiency_choice count="2">
      <text>Choose two skills appropriate for the background. There needn't be a relationship between the skill proficiencies a background grants and the ability scores it increases.</text>
    </skill_proficiency_choice>
    <tool_proficiency_choice count="1">
      <text>Choose one tool used in the practice of the background or often associated with it.</text>
    </tool_proficiency_choice>
    <starting_equipment_custom>
      <text>Assemble a package of equipment worth 50 GP (including unspent gold). Don't include Martial weapons or armor, as characters get them from their class choices.</text>
      <value_limit amount="50" currency="GP"/>
      <restrictions>
        <text>Don't include Martial weapons or armor, as characters get them from their class choices.</text>
      </restrictions>
    </starting_equipment_custom>
  </background>
</compendium>
