<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Ranger [2024]</name>
    <hd>10</hd>
    <proficiency>Strength, Dexterity, Animal Handling, Athletics, Insight, Investigation, Nature, Perception, Stealth, Survival</proficiency>
    <numSkills>3</numSkills>
    <armor>light armor, medium armor, shields</armor>
    <weapons>simple weapons, martial weapons</weapons>
    <tools>none</tools>
    <spellAbility>Wisdom</spellAbility>
    <slotsReset>L</slotsReset>
    <autolevel level="1">
      <slots>0,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <slots>0,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
      <slots>0,3</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4">
      <slots>0,3</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
      <slots>0,4,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <slots>0,4,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
      <slots>0,4,3</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
      <slots>0,4,3</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
      <slots>0,4,3,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <slots>0,4,3,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <slots>0,4,3,3</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12">
      <slots>0,4,3,3</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
      <slots>0,4,3,3,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <slots>0,4,3,3,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <slots>0,4,3,3,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16">
      <slots>0,4,3,3,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <slots>0,4,3,3,3,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <slots>0,4,3,3,3,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19">
      <slots>0,4,3,3,3,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
      <slots>0,4,3,3,3,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <trait>
      <name>Ranger</name>
      <text>far from bustling cities, amid the trees of trackless forests and across wide plains, Rangers keep their unending watch in the wilderness. Rangers learn to track their quarry as a predator does, moving stealthily through the wilds and hiding themselves in brush and rubble.
	Thanks to their connection with nature, Rangers can also cast spells that harness primal powers of the wilderness. A Ranger's talents and magic are honed with deadly focus to protect the world from the ravages of monsters and tyrants.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 119</text>
    </trait>
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Becoming A Ranger As A Level 1 Character</name>
        <text>As a 1st-level Ranger, you begin play with 10 + your Constitution modifier hit points.

Core Ranger Traits
Primary Ability: Dexterity and Wisdom
Hit Point Die: D10 per Ranger level
Saving Throw Proficiencies: Strength and Dexterity
Skill Proficiencies: Choose 3: Animal Handling, Athletics, Insight, Investigation, Nature, Perception, Stealth, or Survival
Weapon Proficiencies: Simple and Martial weapons
Armor Training: Light and Medium armor and Shields
Starting Equipment: Choose A or B: (A) Studded Leather Armor, Scimitar, Shortsword, Longbow, 20 Arrows, Quiver, Druidic Focus (sprig of mistletoe), Explorer's Pack, and 7 GP; or (B) 150GP

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 119</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Becoming A Ranger As A Multiclass Character</name>
        <text>Core Ranger Traits
Primary Ability: Dexterity and Wisdom
Hit Point Die: D10 per Ranger level
Skill Proficiencies: Choose 1: Animal Handling, Athletics, Insight, Investigation, Nature, Perception, Stealth, or Survival
Weapon Proficiencies: Martial weapons
Armor Training: Light and Medium armor and Shields

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 119</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Level 1: Spellcasting</name>
        <text>You have learned to channel the magical essence of nature to cast spells. See chapter 7 for the rules on spellcasting. The information below details how you use those rules with Ranger spells. which appear in the Ranger spell list later in the class's description.

Spell Slots. The Ranger Features table shows how many spell slots you have to cast your level 1+ spells. You regain all expended slots when you finish a Long Rest.

Prepared Spells of Level 1+. You prepare the list of level 1+ spells that are available for you to cast with this feature. To start, choose two level 1 Ranger spells. Cure Wounds and Ensnaring Strike are recommended.
	The number of spells on your list increases as you gain Ranger levels, as shown in the Prepared Spells column of the Ranger Features table. Whenever that number increases, choose additional Ranger spells until the number of spells on your list matches the number in the Ranger Features table. The chosen spells must be of a level for which you have spell slots. For example, if you're a level 5 Ranger, your list of prepared spells can include six Ranger spells of level 1 or 2 in any combination.
	If another Ranger feature gives you spells that you always have prepared, those spells don't count against the number of spells you can prepare with this feature, but those spells otherwise count as Ranger spells for you.

Changing Your Prepared Spells. Whenever you finish a Long Rest, you can replace one spell on your list with another Ranger spell for which you have spell slots.

Spellcasting Ability. Wisdom is your spellcasting ability for your Ranger spells.

Spellcasting Focus. You can use a Druidic Focus as a Spellcasting Focus for your Ranger spells.

<inline_table name="Spells Prepared">
  <header>
    <col label="Level"/>
    <col label="Spells Prepared"/>
  </header>
  <row>
    <cell value="1"/>
    <cell value="2"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="2"/>
    <cell value="3"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="3"/>
    <cell value="4"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="4"/>
    <cell value="5"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="5"/>
    <cell value="6"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="7"/>
    <cell value="7"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="9"/>
    <cell value="9"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="11"/>
    <cell value="10"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="13"/>
    <cell value="11"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="15"/>
    <cell value="12"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="17"/>
    <cell value="14"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="19"/>
    <cell value="15"/>
  </row>
</inline_table>
Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 119</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Level 1: Favored Enemy</name>
        <text>You always have the Hunter's Mark spell prepared. You can cast it twice without expending a spell slot. and you regain all expended uses of this ability when you finish a Long Rest.
	The number of times you can cast the spell without a spell slot increases when you reach certain Ranger levels, as shown in the Favored Enemy column of the Ranger Features table.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 119</text>
        <grants_always_prepared_spell name="Hunter's Mark"/>
        <uses type="scaling_table" table_ref="RangerFeaturesTable_FavoredEnemyColumn" for_spell="Hunter's Mark" without_slot="true" initial_uses="2">
          <recharge type="LR"/>
        </uses>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Level 1: Weapon Mastery</name>
        <text>Your training with weapons allows you to use the mastery properties of two kinds of weapons of your choice with which you have proficiency, such as Longbows and Shortswords.
	Whenever you finish a Long Rest, you can change the kinds of weapons you chose. For example, you could switch to using the mastery properties of Scimitars and Longswords.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 120</text>
        <uses fixed="2" description="kinds_of_weapons_for_mastery_properties"/>
        <recharge type="LR" description="can_change_the_kinds_of_weapons_you_chose"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Favored Enemy</name>
        <value>2</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 2: Deft Explorer</name>
        <text>Thanks to your travels, you gain the following benefits.

Expertise. Choose one of your skill proficiencies with which you lack Expertise. You gain Expertise in that skill.

Languages. You know two languages of your choice from the language tables in chapter 2.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 120</text>
        <benefits>
          <benefit name="Expertise">
            <grants_expertise count="1" type="SkillProficiency" condition="with_which_you_lack_Expertise"/>
          </benefit>
          <benefit name="Languages">
            <grants_language choice_from_table="chapter_2_language_tables" count="2"/>
          </benefit>
        </benefits>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Level 2: Fighting Style</name>
        <text>You gain a Fighting Style feat of your choice (see chapter 5, added as feats). Instead of choosing one of those feats, you can choose the option below.

Druidic Warrior. You learn two Druid cantrips of your choice (see the Druid class's section for a list of Druid spells). Guidance and Starry Wisp are recommended. The chosen cantrips count as Ranger spells for you, and Wisdom is your spellcasting ability for them. Whenever you gain a Ranger level, you can replace one of these cantrips with another Druid cantrip.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 120</text>
        <choice name="Fighting Style Option" count="1">
          <option type="Feat" description="Fighting_Style_feat_of_your_choice"/>
          <option name="Druidic Warrior">
            <grants_spell_learning type="Cantrip" spell_list="Druid" count="2" spellcasting_ability_override="WIS"/>
            <effect description="chosen_cantrips_count_as_Ranger_spells_for_you"/>
            <modifies_spell_choice trigger="whenever_you_gain_a_Ranger_level">
              <effect description="can_replace_one_of_these_cantrips_with_another_Druid_cantrip"/>
            </modifies_spell_choice>
          </option>
        </choice>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 3: Ranger Subclass</name>
        <text>You gain a Ranger subclass of your choice. The Beast Master, Fey Wanderer, Gloom Stalker, and Hunter subclasses are detailed after this class's description. A subclass is a specialization that grants you features at certain Ranger levels. For the rest of your career, you gain each of your subclass's features that are of your Ranger level or lower.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 120</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 4: Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5) or another feat of your choice for which you qualify. You gain this feature again at Ranger levels 8, 12, and 16.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 120</text>
        <asi_options>
          <option description="Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5)"/>
          <option description="Another feat of your choice for which you qualify"/>
        </asi_options>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 5: Extra Attack</name>
        <text>You can attack twice instead of once whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 120</text>
        <modifies_action action_name="Attack" new_attacks_allowed="2"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Favored Enemy</name>
        <value>3</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 6: Roving</name>
        <text>Your Speed increases by 10 feet while you aren't wearing Heavy armor. You also have a Climb Speed and a Swim Speed equal to your Speed.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 121</text>
        <equipment_requirements max_armor_type="medium"/>
        <effect type="SpeedIncrease" value="10"/>
        <effect type="Speed" speed_type="Climb" value_formula="your_Speed"/>
        <effect type="Speed" speed_type="Swim" value_formula="your_Speed"/>
        <modifier category="bonus">speed +10</modifier> <!-- This is a simple representation of the base speed increase -->
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 8: Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5) or another feat of your choice for which you qualify. You gain this feature again at Ranger levels 8, 12, and 16.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 120</text>
        <asi_options>
          <option description="Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5)"/>
          <option description="Another feat of your choice for which you qualify"/>
        </asi_options>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 9: Expertise</name>
        <text>Choose two of your skill proficiencies with which you lack Expertise. You gain Expertise in those skills.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 121</text>
        <grants_expertise count="2" type="SkillProficiency" condition="with_which_you_lack_Expertise"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Favored Enemy</name>
        <value>4</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 10: Tireless</name>
        <text>Primal forces now help fuel you on your journeys, granting you the following benefits.

Temporary Hit Points. As a Magic action, you can give yourself a number of Temporary Hit Points equal to 1d8 plus your Wisdom modifier (minimum of 1). You can use this action a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once), and you regain a ll expended uses when you finish a Long Rest.

Decrease Exhaustion. Whenever you finish a Short Rest, your Exhaustion level, if any, decreases by 1.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 121</text>
        <benefits>
          <benefit name="Temporary Hit Points">
            <action type="MagicAction"/>
            <effect type="GainTemporaryHitPoints" target="self" value_formula="1d8+WIS_modifier" min_value="1"/>
            <uses attribute="WIS" min="1"/>
            <recharge type="LR"/>
          </benefit>
          <benefit name="Decrease Exhaustion">
            <trigger text="whenever_you_finish_a_Short_Rest"/>
            <effect description="your_Exhaustion_level_if_any_decreases_by_1"/>
          </benefit>
        </benefits>
        <roll description="Temporary Hit Points">1d8+%5</roll>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 12: Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5) or another feat of your choice for which you qualify. You gain this feature again at Ranger levels 8, 12, and 16.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 120</text>
        <asi_options>
          <option description="Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5)"/>
          <option description="Another feat of your choice for which you qualify"/>
        </asi_options>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
      <counter>
        <name>Favored Enemy</name>
        <value>5</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 14: Nature's Veil</name>
        <text>You invoke spirits of nature to magically hide yourself. As a Bonus Action, you can give yourself the Invisible condition until the end of your next turn.
	You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once), and you regain a ll expended uses when you finish a Long Rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 121</text>
        <action type="BonusAction"/>
        <effect type="Condition" name="Invisible" target="self" duration="until_end_of_your_next_turn"/>
        <uses attribute="WIS" min="1"/>
        <recharge type="LR"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 16: Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5) or another feat of your choice for which you qualify. You gain this feature again at Ranger levels 8, 12, and 16.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 120</text>
        <asi_options>
          <option description="Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5)"/>
          <option description="Another feat of your choice for which you qualify"/>
        </asi_options>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <counter>
        <name>Favored Enemy</name>
        <value>6</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 18: Feral Senses</name>
        <text>Your connection to the forces of nature grants you Blindsight with a range of 30 feet.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 121</text>
        <effect type="Sense" name="Blindsight" range="30_feet"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 19: Epic Boon</name>
        <text>You gain an Epic Boon feat (see chapter 5) or another feat of your choice for which you qualify. Boon of Dimensional Travel is recommended.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 121</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 20: Foe Slayer</name>
        <text>The damage die of your Hunter's Mark is a d10 rather than a d6.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 121</text>
        <modifies_spell spell_name="Hunter's Mark">
          <modifies_property property="damage_die" new_value="1d10"/>
        </modifies_spell>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Ranger Subclass: Beast Master -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ranger Subclass: Beast Master</name>
        <text>Bond with a Primal Beast

A Beast Master forms a mystical bond with a special animal, drawing on primal magic and a deep connection to the natural world.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 122</text>
        <subclass>Beast Master</subclass>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Primal Companion (Beast Master)</name>
        <text>You magically summon a primal beast, which draws strength from your bond with nature. Choose its stat block: Beast of the Land, Beast of the Sea, or Beast of the Sky. You also determine the kind of animal it is, choosing a kind appropriate for the stat block. Whatever beast you choose, it bears primal markings indicating its supernatural origin.
	The beast is Friendly to you and your allies and obeys your commands. It vanishes if you die.

The Beast in Combat. In combat, the beast acts during your turn. It can move and use its Reaction on its own, but the only action it takes is the Dodge action unless you take a Bonus Action to command it to take an action in its stat block or some other action. You can also sacrifice one of your attacks when you take the Attack action to command t he beast to take the Beast's Strike action. If you h ave the Incapacitated condition, the beast acts on its own and isn't limited to the Dodge action.

Restoring or Replacing the Beast. If the beast has died within the last hour, you can take a Magic action to touch it and expend a spell slot. The beast returns to life after 1 minute with all its Hit Points restored.
	Whenever you finish a Long Rest, you can summon a different primal beast, which appears in an unoccupied space within 5 feet of you. You choose its stat block and appearance. If you already have a beast from this feature, the old one vanishes when the new one appears.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 122</text>
        <subclass>Beast Master</subclass>
        <effect description="magically_summon_a_primal_beast_choose_stat_block_BeastOfTheLand_BeastOfTheSea_or_BeastOfTheSky_determine_animal_kind_bears_primal_markings"/>
        <companion_rules name="Primal Companion">
          <property name="AlignmentAndBehavior" value="Friendly_to_you_and_allies_obeys_commands_vanishes_if_you_die"/>
          <combat_behavior>
            <turn_timing description="acts_during_your_turn"/>
            <movement_and_reaction description="can_move_and_use_its_Reaction_on_its_own"/>
            <action_default type="Dodge"/>
            <command_options>
              <option type="BonusAction" effect="command_it_to_take_an_action_in_its_stat_block_or_some_other_action"/>
              <option type="SacrificeAttack" condition="when_you_take_Attack_action" effect="command_beast_to_take_Beasts_Strike_action"/>
            </command_options>
            <behavior_if_incapacitated description="if_you_have_Incapacitated_condition_beast_acts_on_its_own_isnt_limited_to_Dodge_action"/>
          </combat_behavior>
          <restoring_or_replacing>
            <restore_option condition="if_beast_died_within_last_hour">
              <action type="MagicAction" to_touch_beast="true"/>
              <cost type="SpellSlot" value_any="true"/>
              <effect description="beast_returns_to_life_after_1_minute_with_all_HP_restored"/>
            </restore_option>
            <replace_option trigger="whenever_you_finish_a_Long_Rest">
              <effect description="can_summon_a_different_primal_beast_appears_in_unoccupied_space_within_5_feet_choose_stat_block_and_appearance_old_one_vanishes"/>
            </replace_option>
          </restoring_or_replacing>
        </companion_rules>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 7: Exceptional Training (Beast Master)</name>
        <text>When you take a Bonus Action to command your Primal Companion beast to take an action, you can also command it to take the Dash, Disengage, Dodge, or Help action using its Bonus Action.
	In addition, whenever it hits with an attack roll and deals damage, it can deal your choice of Force damage or its normal damage type.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 123</text>
        <subclass>Beast Master</subclass>
        <enhances_feature feature_name="Level 3: Primal Companion (Beast Master)">
          <command_enhancement>
            <trigger text="when_you_take_a_Bonus_Action_to_command_your_Primal_Companion_beast_to_take_an_action"/>
            <effect description="can_also_command_it_to_take_the_Dash_Disengage_Dodge_or_Help_action_using_its_Bonus_Action"/>
          </command_enhancement>
          <damage_modification>
            <trigger text="whenever_Primal_Companion_hits_with_an_attack_roll_and_deals_damage"/>
            <effect description="it_can_deal_your_choice_of_Force_damage_or_its_normal_damage_type"/>
          </damage_modification>
        </enhances_feature>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 11: Bestial Fury (Beast Master)</name>
        <text>When you command your Primal Companion beast to take the Beast's Strike action, the beast can use it twice.
	In addition, the first time each turn it hits a creature under the effect of your Hunter's Mark spell, the beast deals extra Force damage equal to the bonus damage of that spell.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 123</text>
        <subclass>Beast Master</subclass>
        <enhances_feature feature_name="Level 3: Primal Companion (Beast Master)">
          <command_enhancement for_action="BeastsStrike">
            <effect description="the_beast_can_use_it_twice"/>
          </command_enhancement>
          <damage_enhancement>
            <trigger text="first_time_each_turn_Primal_Companion_hits_a_creature_under_effect_of_your_Hunters_Mark_spell"/>
            <effect type="ExtraDamage" damage_type="Force" value_formula="bonus_damage_of_Hunters_Mark_spell"/>
          </damage_enhancement>
        </enhances_feature>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 15: Share Spells (Beast Master)</name>
        <text>When you cast a spell targeting yourself, you can also affect your Primal Companion beast with the spell if the beast is within 30 feet of you.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 123</text>
        <subclass>Beast Master</subclass>
        <trigger text="when_you_cast_a_spell_targeting_yourself"/>
        <condition text="if_Primal_Companion_beast_is_within_30_feet_of_you"/>
        <effect description="can_also_affect_your_Primal_Companion_beast_with_the_spell"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Ranger Subclass: Fey Wanderer -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ranger Subclass: Fey Wanderer</name>
        <text>Wield Fey Mirth and Fury

A fey mystique surrounds you, thanks to the boon of an archfey or a location in the Feywild that transformed you. However you gained fey magic, you are now a Fey Wanderer. Your joyful laughter brightens the hearts of the downtrodden, and your martial prowess strikes terror in your foes, for great is the mirth of the fey and dreadful is their fury.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 123</text>
        <subclass>Fey Wanderer</subclass>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Dreadful Strikes (Fey Wanderer)</name>
        <text>You can augment your weapon strikes with mind-scarring magic drawn from the murky hollows of the Feywild. When you hit a creature with a weapon, you can deal an extra 1d4 Psychic damage to the target, which can take this extra damage only once per turn. The extra damage increases to 1d6 when you reach Ranger level 11.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 123</text>
        <subclass>Fey Wanderer</subclass>
        <trigger text="when_you_hit_a_creature_with_a_weapon"/>
        <effect type="ExtraDamage" damage_type="Psychic" value_dice="1d4">
          <scaling level="11" dice="1d6"/>
        </effect>
        <restriction text="target_can_take_this_extra_damage_only_once_per_turn"/>
        <roll description="Psychic Damage" level="3">1d4</roll>
        <roll description="Psychic Damage" level="11">1d6</roll>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Fey Wanderer Spells (Fey Wanderer)</name>
        <text>When you reach a Ranger level specified in the Fey Wanderer Spells table, you thereafter always have the listed spells prepared.

<inline_table name="Fey Wanderer Spells">
  <header>
    <col label="Ranger Level"/>
    <col label="Spell"/>
  </header>
  <row>
    <cell value="3"/>
    <cell value="Charm Person"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="5"/>
    <cell value="Misty Step"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="9"/>
    <cell value="Summon Fey"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="13"/>
    <cell value="Dimension Door"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="17"/>
    <cell value="Mislead"/>
  </row>
</inline_table>
You also possess a fey blessing. Choose it from the Feywild Gifts table or determine it randomly.

<inline_table name="Feywild Gifts">
  <header>
    <col label="1d6"/>
    <col label="Gift"/>
  </header>
  <row>
    <cell value="1"/>
    <cell value="Illusory butterflies flutter around you while you take a Short or Long Rest."/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="2"/>
    <cell value="Flowers bloom from your hair each dawn."/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="3"/>
    <cell value="You faintly smell of cinnamon, lavender, nutmeg, or another comforting herb or spice."/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="4"/>
    <cell value="Your shadow dances while no one is looking directly at it."/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="5"/>
    <cell value="Horns or antlers sprout from your head."/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="6"/>
    <cell value="Your skin and hair change color each dawn."/>
  </row>
</inline_table>
Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 123</text>
        <subclass>Fey Wanderer</subclass>
        <grants_always_prepared_spell name="Charm Person" level_gained_at="3"/>
        <grants_always_prepared_spell name="Misty Step" level_gained_at="5"/>
        <grants_always_prepared_spell name="Summon Fey" level_gained_at="9"/>
        <grants_always_prepared_spell name="Dimension Door" level_gained_at="13"/>
        <grants_always_prepared_spell name="Mislead" level_gained_at="17"/>
        <choice name="Feywild Gift" from_table_ref="Feywild Gifts" random_roll="1d6"/>
        <roll description="Feywild Gift">1d6</roll>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Otherworldly Glamour (Fey Wanderer)</name>
        <text>Whenever you make a Charisma check, you gain a bonus to the check equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of +1).
	You also gain proficiency in one of these skills of your choice: Deception, Performance, or Persuasion.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 123</text>
        <subclass>Fey Wanderer</subclass>
        <trigger text="whenever_you_make_a_Charisma_check"/>
        <effect type="Bonus" value_formula="WIS_modifier" min_value="1"/>
        <grants_proficiency type="Skill" choice_from_list="Deception,Performance,Persuasion" count="1"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 7: Beguiling Twist (Fey Wanderer)</name>
        <text>The magic of the Feywild guards your mind. You have Advantage on saving throws to avoid or end the Charmed or Frightened condition.
	In addition, whenever you or a creature you can see within 120 feet of you succeeds on a saving throw to avoid or end the Charmed or Frightened condition, you can take a Reaction to force a different creature you can see within 120 feet of yourself to make a Wisdom save against your spell save DC. On a failed save, the target is Charmed or Frightened (your choice) for 1 minute. The target repeats the save at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 125</text>
        <subclass>Fey Wanderer</subclass>
        <effect type="Advantage" on="saving_throws_to_avoid_or_end_Charmed_or_Frightened_condition"/>
        <action type="Reaction">
          <trigger text="whenever_you_or_a_creature_you_can_see_within_120_feet_of_you_succeeds_on_a_saving_throw_to_avoid_or_end_the_Charmed_or_Frightened_condition"/>
          <target description="a_different_creature_you_can_see_within_120_feet"/>
          <effect description="force_target_to_make_a_Wisdom_save_against_your_spell_save_DC">
            <on_failed_save type="Condition" name_choice="Charmed_or_Frightened" duration="1_minute" save_type="WIS" save_timing="end_of_targets_turn" save_ends_effect="true"/>
          </effect>
        </action>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 11: Fey Reinforcements (Fey Wanderer)</name>
        <text>You can cast Summon Fey without a Material component. You can also cast it once without a spell slot, and you regain the ability to cast it in this way when you finish a Long Rest.
	Whenever you start casting the spell, you can modify it so that it doesn't require Concentration. If you do so, the spell's duration becomes 1 minute for that casting.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 125</text>
        <subclass>Fey Wanderer</subclass>
        <modifies_spell spell_name="Summon Fey">
          <can_cast_without_material_component="true"/>
          <option_to_modify_casting>
            <effect description="doesnt_require_Concentration_duration_becomes_1_minute"/>
          </option_to_modify_casting>
        </modifies_spell>
        <uses fixed="1" for_casting_spell="Summon Fey" without_slot="true">
          <recharge type="LR"/>
        </uses>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 15: Misty Wanderer (Fey Wanderer)</name>
        <text>You can cast Misty Step without expending a spell slot. You can do so a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a Long Rest.
	In addition, whenever you cast Misty Step, you can bring along one willing creature you can see within 5 feet of yourself. That creature teleports to an unoccupied space of your choice within 5 feet of your destination space.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 125</text>
        <subclass>Fey Wanderer</subclass>
        <uses attribute="WIS" min="1" for_casting_spell="Misty Step" without_slot="true">
          <recharge type="LR"/>
        </uses>
        <modifies_spell spell_name="Misty Step">
          <trigger text="whenever_you_cast_Misty_Step"/>
          <effect description="can_bring_along_one_willing_creature_you_can_see_within_5_feet_That_creature_teleports_to_an_unoccupied_space_of_your_choice_within_5_feet_of_your_destination_space"/>
        </modifies_spell>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Ranger Subclass: Gloom Stalker -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ranger Subclass: Gloom Stalker</name>
        <text>Draw on Shadow Magic to Fight Your Foes

Gloom Stalkers are at home in the darkest places, wielding magic drawn from the Shadowfell to combat enemies that lurk in darkness.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 125</text>
        <subclass>Gloom Stalker</subclass>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Dread Ambusher (Gloom Stalker)</name>
        <text>You have mastered the art of creating fearsome ambushes, granting you the following benefits.

Ambusher's Leap. At the start of your first turn of each combat, your Speed increases by 10 feet until the end of that turn.

Dreadful Strike. When you attack a creature and hit it with a weapon, you can deal an extra 2d6 Psychic damage. You can use this benefit only once per turn, you can use it a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a Long Rest.

Initiative Bonus. When you roll Initiative, you can add your Wisdom modifier to the roll.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 125</text>
        <subclass>Gloom Stalker</subclass>
        <benefits>
          <benefit name="Ambusher's Leap">
            <trigger text="at_the_start_of_your_first_turn_of_each_combat"/>
            <effect type="SpeedIncrease" value="10" duration="until_end_of_that_turn"/>
          </benefit>
          <benefit name="Dreadful Strike">
            <uses fixed="1" per_turn="true"/>
            <trigger text="when_you_attack_a_creature_and_hit_it_with_a_weapon"/>
            <effect type="ExtraDamage" damage_type="Psychic" value_dice="2d6"/> <!-- Scales with Stalker's Flurry -->
            <uses attribute="WIS" min="1"/>
            <recharge type="LR"/>
          </benefit>
          <benefit name="Initiative Bonus">
            <trigger text="when_you_roll_Initiative"/>
            <effect type="Bonus" value_formula="WIS_modifier" on="the_roll"/>
          </benefit>
        </benefits>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Gloom Stalker Spells (Gloom Stalker)</name>
        <text>When you reach a Ranger level specified in the Gloom Stalker Spells table, you thereafter always have the listed spells prepared.

<inline_table name="Gloom Stalker Spells">
  <header>
    <col label="Ranger Level"/>
    <col label="Spells"/>
  </header>
  <row>
    <cell value="3"/>
    <cell value="Disguise Self"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="5"/>
    <cell value="Rope Trick"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="9"/>
    <cell value="Fear"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="13"/>
    <cell value="Greater Invisibility"/>
  </row>
  <row>
    <cell value="17"/>
    <cell value="Seeming"/>
  </row>
</inline_table>
Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 126</text>
        <subclass>Gloom Stalker</subclass>
        <grants_always_prepared_spell name="Disguise Self" level_gained_at="3"/>
        <grants_always_prepared_spell name="Rope Trick" level_gained_at="5"/>
        <grants_always_prepared_spell name="Fear" level_gained_at="9"/>
        <grants_always_prepared_spell name="Greater Invisibility" level_gained_at="13"/>
        <grants_always_prepared_spell name="Seeming" level_gained_at="17"/>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Umbral Sight (Gloom Stalker)</name>
        <text>You gain Darkvision with a range of 60 feet. If you already have Darkvision when you gain this feature, its range increases by 60 feet.
	You are also adept at evading creatures that rely on Darkvision. While entirely in Darkness. you have the Invisible condition to any creature that relies on Darkvision to see you in that Darkness.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 126</text>
        <subclass>Gloom Stalker</subclass>
        <effect type="Sense" name="Darkvision" range="60_feet"/>
        <enhancement condition="if_already_have_Darkvision" effect="its_range_increases_by_60_feet"/>
        <condition text="while_entirely_in_Darkness"/>
        <effect type="Condition" name="Invisible" to_creatures="any_creature_that_relies_on_Darkvision_to_see_you_in_that_Darkness"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 7: Iron Mind (Gloom Stalker)</name>
        <text>You have honed your ability to resist mind-altering powers. You gain proficiency in Wisdom saving throws. If you already have this proficiency, you instead gain proficiency in Intelligence or Charisma saving throws (your choice).

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 126</text>
        <subclass>Gloom Stalker</subclass>
        <grants_proficiency type="SavingThrow" name="Wisdom"/>
        <alternative_grant condition="if_already_proficient_in_Wisdom_saves">
          <grants_proficiency type="SavingThrow" choice_from_list="Intelligence,Charisma" count="1"/>
        </alternative_grant>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 11: Stalker's Flurry (Gloom Stalker)</name>
        <text>The Psychic damage of your Dreadful Strike becomes 2d8. In addition, when you use the Dreadful Strike effect of your Dread Ambusher feature, you can cause one of the following additional effects.

Sudden Strike. You can make another attack with the same weapon against a different creature that is within 5 feet of the original target and that is within the weapon's range.

Mass Fear. The target and each creature within 10 feet of it must make a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, a creature has the Frightened condition until the start of your next turn.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 126</text>
        <subclass>Gloom Stalker</subclass>
        <enhances_feature feature_name="Level 3: Dread Ambusher (Gloom Stalker)" benefit_name="Dreadful Strike">
          <modifies_effect type="ExtraDamage" new_value_dice="2d8"/>
          <trigger text="when_you_use_the_Dreadful_Strike_effect"/>
          <choice name="StalkersFlurryAdditionalEffect" count="1">
            <option name="Sudden Strike">
              <effect description="make_another_attack_with_the_same_weapon_against_a_different_creature_that_is_within_5_feet_of_the_original_target_and_that_is_within_the_weapons_range"/>
            </option>
            <option name="Mass Fear">
              <target description="the_target_and_each_creature_within_10_feet_of_it"/>
              <effect description="must_make_a_Wisdom_saving_throw_against_your_spell_save_DC">
                <on_failed_save type="Condition" name="Frightened" duration="until_start_of_your_next_turn"/>
              </effect>
            </option>
          </choice>
        </enhances_feature>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 15: Shadowy Dodge (Gloom Stalker)</name>
        <text>When a creature makes an attack roll against you, you can take a Reaction to impose Disadvantage on that roll. Whether the attack hits or misses, you can then teleport up to 30 feet to an unoccupied space you can see.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 126</text>
        <subclass>Gloom Stalker</subclass>
        <action type="Reaction"/>
        <trigger text="when_a_creature_makes_an_attack_roll_against_you"/>
        <effect type="Disadvantage" on="that_roll"/>
        <effect type="Teleport" target="self" range="up_to_30_feet" destination="unoccupied_space_you_can_see" timing="whether_attack_hits_or_misses"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Ranger Subclass: Hunter -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Ranger Subclass: Hunter</name>
        <text>Protect Nature and People from Destruction

You stalk prey in the wilds and elsewhere, using your abilities as a Hunter to protect nature and people everywhere from forces that would destroy them.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 127</text>
        <subclass>Hunter</subclass>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Hunter's Lore (Hunter)</name>
        <text>You can call on the forces of nature to reveal certain strengths and weaknesses of your prey. While a creature is marked by your Hunter's Mark, you know whether that creature has any Immunities, Resistances, or Vulnerabilities, and if the creature has any, you know what they are.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 127</text>
        <subclass>Hunter</subclass>
        <trigger text="while_a_creature_is_marked_by_your_Hunters_Mark"/>
        <effect description="you_know_whether_that_creature_has_any_Immunities_Resistances_or_Vulnerabilities_and_if_it_has_any_you_know_what_they_are"/>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Hunter's Prey (Hunter)</name>
        <text>You gain one of the following feature options of your choice. Whenever you finish a Short or Long Rest, you can replace the chosen option with the other one.

Colossus Slayer. Your tenacity can wear down even the most resilient foes. When you hit a creature with a weapon, the weapon deals an extra 1d8 damage to the target if it's missing any of its Hit Points. You can deal t his extra damage only once per turn.

Horde Breaker. Once on each of your turns when you make an attack with a weapon, you can make another attack with the same weapon against a different creature that is within 5 feet of the original target, that is within the weapon's range, and that you haven't attacked this turn.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 127</text>
        <subclass>Hunter</subclass>
        <choice name="HuntersPreyOption" count="1">
          <recharge type="SR_or_LR" description="can_replace_chosen_option_with_the_other_one"/>
          <option name="Colossus Slayer">
            <uses fixed="1" per_turn="true"/>
            <trigger text="when_you_hit_a_creature_with_a_weapon"/>
            <condition text="if_target_is_missing_any_of_its_Hit_Points"/>
            <effect type="ExtraDamage" value="1d8" damage_type_same_as_weapon="true"/>
          </option>
          <option name="Horde Breaker">
            <uses fixed="1" per_turn="true"/>
            <trigger text="when_you_make_an_attack_with_a_weapon"/>
            <effect description="can_make_another_attack_with_the_same_weapon_against_a_different_creature_that_is_within_5_feet_of_original_target_within_weapons_range_and_not_attacked_this_turn"/>
          </option>
        </choice>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 7: Defensive Tactics (Hunter)</name>
        <text>You gain one of the following feature options of your choice. Whenever you finish a Short or Long Rest, you can replace the chosen option with the other one.

Escape the Horde. Opportunity Attacks have Disadvantage against you.

Multiattack Defense. When a creature hits you with an attack roll, that creature has Disadvantage on all other attack rolls against you this turn.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 127</text>
        <subclass>Hunter</subclass>
        <choice name="DefensiveTacticsOption" count="1">
          <recharge type="SR_or_LR" description="can_replace_chosen_option_with_the_other_one"/>
          <option name="Escape the Horde">
            <effect type="Disadvantage" on="Opportunity_Attacks_against_you"/>
          </option>
          <option name="Multiattack Defense">
            <trigger text="when_a_creature_hits_you_with_an_attack_roll"/>
            <effect type="Disadvantage" target="that_creature" on="all_other_attack_rolls_against_you_this_turn"/>
          </option>
        </choice>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 11: Superior Hunter's Prey (Hunter)</name>
        <text>Once per turn when you deal damage to a creature marked by your Hunter's Mark, you can also deal that spell's extra damage to a different creature that you can see within 30 feet of the first creature.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 127</text>
        <subclass>Hunter</subclass>
        <uses fixed="1" per_turn="true"/>
        <trigger text="when_you_deal_damage_to_a_creature_marked_by_your_Hunters_Mark"/>
        <effect description="can_also_deal_that_spells_extra_damage_to_a_different_creature_that_you_can_see_within_30_feet_of_the_first_creature"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 15: Superior Hunter's Defense (Hunter)</name>
        <text>When you take damage, you can take a Reaction to give yourself Resistance to that damage and any other damage of the same type until the end of the current turn.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 127</text>
        <subclass>Hunter</subclass>
        <action type="Reaction"/>
        <trigger text="when_you_take_damage"/>
        <effect type="Resistance" damage_types="that_damage_and_any_other_damage_of_the_same_type" duration="until_end_of_current_turn"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
