<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Sorcerer [2024]</name>
    <hd>6</hd>
    <proficiency>Constitution, Charisma, Arcana, Deception, Insight, Intimidation, Persuasion, Religion</proficiency>
    <numSkills>2</numSkills>
    <armor>none</armor>
    <weapons>Simple weapons</weapons>
    <tools>none</tools>
    <spellAbility>Charisma</spellAbility>
    <slotsReset>L</slotsReset>
    <autolevel level="1">
      <slots>4,2</slots> <!-- Cantrips, Level 1 slots -->
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <slots>4,3</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
      <slots>4,4,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4">
      <slots>5,4,3</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
      <slots>5,4,3,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <slots>5,4,3,3</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
      <slots>5,4,3,3,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
      <slots>5,4,3,3,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
      <slots>5,4,3,3,3,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <slots>6,4,3,3,3,2</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <slots>6,4,3,3,3,2,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12">
      <slots>6,4,3,3,3,2,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
      <slots>6,4,3,3,3,2,1,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <slots>6,4,3,3,3,2,1,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <slots>6,4,3,3,3,2,1,1,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16">
      <slots>6,4,3,3,3,2,1,1,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <slots>6,4,3,3,3,2,1,1,1,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <slots>6,4,3,3,3,3,1,1,1,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19">
      <slots>6,4,3,3,3,3,2,1,1,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
      <slots>6,4,3,3,3,3,2,2,1,1</slots>
    </autolevel>
    <trait>
      <name>Sorcerer</name>
      <text>Sorcerers wield innate magic that is stamped into their being. Some Sorcerers can't name the origin of their power, while others trace it to strange events in their personal or family history. The blessing of a dragon or a dryad at a baby's birth or the strike of lightning from a clear sky might spark a Sorcerer's gift. So too might the gift of a deity, exposure to the strange magic of another plane of existence, or a glimpse into the inner workings of reality. Whatever the origin, the result is an indelible mark on the Sorcerer, a churning magic that can be passed down through generations.
	Sorcerers don't learn magic; the raw, roiling power of magic is part of them. The essential art of a Sorcerer is learning to harness and channel that innate magic, allowing the Sorcerer to discover new and staggering ways to unleash their power. As Sorcerers master their innate magic, they grow more attuned to its origin, developing distinct powers that reflect its source.
	Sorcerers are rare. Some family lines produce exactly one Sorcerer in every generation, but most of the time, the talents of sorcery appear as a fluke. People who have this magical power soon discover that it doesn't like to stay quiet. A Sorcerer's magic wants to be wielded.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 139</text>
    </trait>
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Becoming A Sorcerer As A Level 1 Character</name>
        <text>As a 1st-level Sorcerer, you begin play with 6 + your Constitution modifier hit points.

Core Sorcerer Traits
Primary Ability: Charisma
Hit Point Die: D6 per Sorcerer level
Saving Throw Proficiencies: Constitution and Charisma
Skill Proficiencies: Choose 2: Arcana, Deception, Insight, Intimidation, Persuasion, or Religion
Weapon Proficiencies: Simple weapons
Armor Training: None
Starting Equipment: Choose A or 8: (A) Spear, 2 Daggers, Arcane Focus (crystal), Dungeoneer's Pack, and 28 GP; or (B) 50 GP

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 139</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Becoming A Sorcerer As A Multiclass Character</name>
        <text>Core Sorcerer Traits
Primary Ability: Charisma
Hit Point Die: D6 per Sorcerer level

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 139</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Level 1: Spellcasting</name>
        <text>Drawing from your innate magic, you can cast spells. See chapter 7 for the rules on spellcasting. The information below details how you use those rules with Sorcerer spells, which appear in the Sorcerer spell list later in the class's description.

Cantrips. You know four Sorcerer cantrips of your choice. Light, Prestidigitation, Shocking Grasp, and Sorcerous Burst are recommended. Whenever you gain a Sorcerer level, you can replace one of your cantrips from this feature with another Sorcerer cantrip of your choice.
	When you reach Sorcerer levels 4 and 10, you learn another Sorcerer cantrip of your choice, as shown in the Cantrips column of the Sorcerer Features table.

Spell Slots. The Sorcerer Features table shows how many spell slots you have to cast your level 1+ spells. You regain all expended slots when you finish a Long Rest.

Prepared Spells of Level 1+. You prepare the list of level 1+ spells that are available for you to cast with this feature. To start, choose two level 1 Sorcerer spells. Burning Hands and Detect Magic are recommended.
	The number of spells on your list increases as you gain Sorcerer levels, as shown in the Prepared Spells column of the Sorcerer Features table. Whenever that number increases, choose additional Sorcerer spells until the number of spells on your list matches the number in the Sorcerer Features table. The chosen spells must be of a level for which you have spell slots. For example, if you're a level 3 Sorcerer, your list of prepared spells can include six Sorcerer spells of level 1 or 2 in any combination.
	If another Sorcerer feature gives you spells that you always have prepared, those spells don't count against the number of spells you can prepare with this feature, but those spells otherwise count as Sorcerer spells for you.

Changing Your Prepared Spells. Whenever you gain a Sorcerer level, you can replace one spell on your list with another Sorcerer spell for which you have spell slots.

Spellcasting Ability. Charisma is your spellcasting ability for your Sorcerer spells.

Spellcasting Focus. You can use an Arcane Focus as a Spellcasting Focus for your Sorcerer spells.

Spells Prepared:
Level | Prepared Spells
1 | 2
2 | 4
3 | 6
4 | 7
5 | 9
6 | 10
7 | 11
8 | 12
9 | 14
10 | 15
11 | 16
12 | 16
13 | 17
14 | 17
15 | 18
16 | 18
17 | 19
18 | 20
19 | 21
20 | 22

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 139</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Level 1: Innate Sorcery</name>
        <text>An event in your past left an indelible mark on you, infusing you with simmering magic. As a Bonus Action, you can unleash that magic for 1 minute, during which you gain the following benefits:

	• The spell save DC of your Sorcerer spells increases by 1.
	• You have Advantage on the attack rolls of Sorcerer spells you cast.

You can use this feature twice, and you regain all expended uses of it when you finish a Long Rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 140</text>
        <action type="BonusAction"/>
        <effect type="Buff" name="InnateSorceryBuff" duration="1_minute">
          <benefits>
            <benefit description="spell_save_DC_of_your_Sorcerer_spells_increases_by_1"/>
            <benefit type="Advantage" on="attack_rolls_of_Sorcerer_spells_you_cast"/>
          </benefits>
        </effect>
        <uses fixed="2"/>
        <recharge type="LR"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Innate Sorcery</name>
        <value>2</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 2: Font of Magic</name>
        <text>You can tap into the wellspring of magic within yourself. This wellspring is represented by Sorcery Points, which allow you to create a variety of magical effects.
	You have 2 Sorcery Points, and you gain more as you reach higher levels, as shown in the Sorcery Points column of the Sorcerer Features table. You can't have more Sorcery Points than the number shown in the table for your level. You regain all expended Sorcery Points when you finish a Long Rest.
	You can use your Sorcery Points to fuel the options below, along with other features, such as Metamagic, that use those points.

Converting Spell Slots to Sorcery Points. You can expend a spell slot to gain a number of Sorcery Points equal to the slot's level (no action required).

Creating Spell Slots. As a Bonus Action, you can transform unexpended Sorcery Points into one spell slot. The Creating Spell Slots table shows the cost of creating a spell slot of a given level, and it lists the minimum Sorcerer level you must be to create a slot. You can create a spell slot no higher than level 5.
	Any spell slot you create with this feature vanishes when you finish a Long Rest.

Creating Spell Slots:
Spell Slot Level | Sorcery Point Cost | Min. Sorcerer Level
1 | 2 | 2
2 | 3 | 3
3 | 5 | 5
4 | 6 | 7
5 | 7 | 9

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 140</text>
        <resource name="SorceryPoints" scaling_table="SorcererFeaturesTable_SorceryPointsColumn" initial_points="2">
          <recharge type="LR"/>
        </resource>
        <flexible_casting>
          <option name="ConvertToSorceryPoints">
            <action type="NoAction"/>
            <cost type="SpellSlot" value_variable="spell_slot_level"/>
            <effect description="gain_Sorcery_Points_equal_to_slots_level"/>
          </option>
          <option name="CreateSpellSlots">
            <action type="BonusAction"/>
            <!-- The value_from_table attribute will now implicitly reference the inline_table below -->
            <cost type="SorceryPoints" value_from_table="Creating Spell Slots Table"/>
            <effect description="transform_unexpended_Sorcery_Points_into_one_spell_slot_max_level_5"/>
            <note text="any_spell_slot_created_vanishes_on_Long_Rest"/>
            <inline_table name="Creating Spell Slots Table">
              <header>
                <col label="Spell Slot Level"/>
                <col label="Sorcery Point Cost"/>
                <col label="Min. Sorcerer Level"/>
              </header>
              <row><cell value="1"/><cell value="2"/><cell value="2"/></row>
              <row><cell value="2"/><cell value="3"/><cell value="3"/></row>
              <row><cell value="3"/><cell value="5"/><cell value="5"/></row>
              <row><cell value="4"/><cell value="6"/><cell value="7"/></row>
              <row><cell value="5"/><cell value="7"/><cell value="9"/></row>
            </inline_table>
          </option>
        </flexible_casting>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Level 2: Metamagic</name>
        <text>Because your magic flows from within, you can alter your spells to suit your needs; you gain two Meta magic options of your choice from "Metamagic Options" later in this class's description (added as spells in the Metamagic Options spell list). You use the chosen options to temporarily modify spells you cast. To use an option, you must spend the number of Sorcery Points that it costs.
	You can use only one Metamagic option on a spell when you cast it unless otherwise noted in one of those options.
	Whenever you gain a Sorcerer level, you can replace one of your Metamagic options with one you don't know. You gain two more options at Sorcerer level 10 and two more at Sorcerer level 17.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 141</text>
        <learns_metamagic_options count_initial="2">
          <scaling level="10" additional_count="2"/>
          <scaling level="17" additional_count="2"/>
          <note text="whenever_you_gain_a_Sorcerer_level_you_can_replace_one_of_your_Metamagic_options_with_one_you_dont_know"/>
        </learns_metamagic_options>
        <restriction text="can_use_only_one_Metamagic_option_on_a_spell_when_you_cast_it_unless_otherwise_noted"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>2</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 3: Sorcerer Subclass</name>
        <text>You gain a Sorcerer subclass of your choice. The Aberrant Sorcery, Clockwork Sorcery, Draconic Sorcery, and Wild Magic Sorcery subclasses are detailed after this class's description. A subclass is a specialization that grants you features at certain Sorcerer levels. For the rest of your career, you gain each of your subclass's features that are of your Sorcerer level or lower.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 141</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>3</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 4: Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5) or another feat of your choice for which you qualify. You gain this feature again at Sorcerer levels 8, 12, and 16.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 141</text>
        <asi_options>
          <option description="Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5)"/>
          <option description="Another feat of your choice for which you qualify"/>
        </asi_options>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>4</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 5: Sorcerous Restoration</name>
        <text>When you finish a Short Rest, you can regain expended Sorcery Points, but no more than a number equal to half your Sorcerer level (round down). Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a Long Rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 141</text>
        <trigger text="when_you_finish_a_Short_Rest"/>
        <effect description="regain_expended_Sorcery_Points_up_to_half_Sorcerer_level_round_down"/>
        <uses fixed="1"/>
        <recharge type="LR"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcerous Restoration</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>5</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>6</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 7: Sorcery Incarnate</name>
        <text>If you have no uses of Innate Sorcery left, you can use it if you spend 2 Sorcery Points when you take the Bonus Action to activate it.

In addition, while your Innate Sorcery feature is active, you can use up to two of your Metamagic options on each spell you cast.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 141</text>
        <enhances_feature feature_name="Level 1: Innate Sorcery">
          <alternative_activation_cost>
            <condition text="if_you_have_no_uses_of_Innate_Sorcery_left"/>
            <cost resource="SorceryPoints" value="2" on_bonus_action_activation="true"/>
          </alternative_activation_cost>
          <benefit_while_active>
            <effect description="can_use_up_to_two_of_your_Metamagic_options_on_each_spell_you_cast"/>
          </benefit_while_active>
        </enhances_feature>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>7</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 8: Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5) or another feat of your choice for which you qualify. You gain this feature again at Sorcerer levels 8, 12, and 16.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 141</text>
        <asi_options>
          <option description="Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5)"/>
          <option description="Another feat of your choice for which you qualify"/>
        </asi_options>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>8</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>9</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>10</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>11</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 12: Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5) or another feat of your choice for which you qualify. You gain this feature again at Sorcerer levels 8, 12, and 16.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 141</text>
        <asi_options>
          <option description="Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5)"/>
          <option description="Another feat of your choice for which you qualify"/>
        </asi_options>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>12</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>13</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>14</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>15</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 16: Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5) or another feat of your choice for which you qualify. You gain this feature again at Sorcerer levels 8, 12, and 16.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 141</text>
        <asi_options>
          <option description="Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5)"/>
          <option description="Another feat of your choice for which you qualify"/>
        </asi_options>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>16</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>17</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>18</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 19: Epic Boon</name>
        <text>You gain an Epic Boon feat (see chapter 5) or another feat of your choice for which you qualify. Boon of Dimensional Travel is recommended.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 141</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>19</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 20: Arcane Apotheosis</name>
        <text>While your Innate Sorcery feature is active, you can use one Metamagic option on each of your turns without spending Sorcery Points on it.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 141</text>
        <enhances_feature feature_name="Level 1: Innate Sorcery">
          <benefit_while_active>
            <effect description="can_use_one_Metamagic_option_on_each_of_your_turns_without_spending_Sorcery_Points_on_it"/>
          </benefit_while_active>
        </enhances_feature>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Sorcery Points</name>
        <value>20</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Sorcerer Subclass: Aberrant Sorcery -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Sorcerer Subclass: Aberrant Sorcery</name>
        <text>Wield Unnatural Psionic Power

An alien influence has wrapped its tendrils around your mind, giving you psionic power. You can now touch other minds with that power and alter the world around you. Will this power shine from you as a hopeful beacon to others? Or will you be a terror to those who feel the stab of your mind?
	Perhaps a psychic wind from the Astral Plane carried psionic energy to you, or you were exposed to the Far Realm's warping influence. Alternatively, you were implanted with a mind flayer tadpole, but your transformation into a mind flayer never occurred; now the tadpole's psionic power is yours. However you acquired this power, your mind is aflame with it.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 145</text>
        <subclass>Aberrant Sorcery</subclass>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Psionic Spells (Aberrant Sorcery)</name>
        <text>When you reach a Sorcerer level specified in the Psionic Spells table, you thereafter always have the listed spells prepared.

Psionic Spells:
Sorcerer Level | Spells
3 | Arms of Hadar, Calm Emotions, Detect Thoughts, Dissonant Whispers, Mind Sliver
5 | Hunger of Hadar, Sending
7 | Evard's Black Tentacles, Summon Aberration
9 | Rory's Telepathic Bond, Telekinesis

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 145</text>
        <subclass>Aberrant Sorcery</subclass>
        <inline_table name="Psionic Spells">
          <header>
            <col label="Sorcerer Level"/>
            <col label="Spells"/>
          </header>
          <row>
            <cell value="3"/>
            <cell value="Arms of Hadar, Calm Emotions, Detect Thoughts, Dissonant Whispers, Mind Sliver"/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell value="5"/>
            <cell value="Hunger of Hadar, Sending"/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell value="7"/>
            <cell value="Evard's Black Tentacles, Summon Aberration"/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell value="9"/>
            <cell value="Rory's Telepathic Bond, Telekinesis"/>
          </row>
        </inline_table>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Telepathic Speech (Aberrant Sorcery)</name>
        <text>You can form a telepathic connection between your mind and the mind of another. As a Bonus Action, choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of yourself. You and the chosen creature can communicate telepathically with each other while the two of you are within a number of miles of each other equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of 1 mile). To understand each other, you each must mentally use a language the other knows.
	The telepathic connection lasts for a number of minutes equal to your Sorcerer level. It ends early if you use this ability to form a connection with a different creature.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 145</text>
        <subclass>Aberrant Sorcery</subclass>
        <action type="BonusAction"/>
        <target description="one_creature_you_can_see_within_30_feet"/>
        <effect type="TelepathicCommunication" range_miles_formula="CHA_modifier_min_1" duration_minutes_formula="SorcererLevel">
          <restriction text="to_understand_each_other_you_each_must_mentally_use_a_language_the_other_knows"/>
          <ends_early_if condition="you_use_this_ability_to_form_a_connection_with_a_different_creature"/>
        </effect>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 6: Psionic Sorcery (Aberrant Sorcery)</name>
        <text>When you cast any level 1+ spell from your Psionic Spells feature, you can cast it by expending a spell slot as normal or by spending a number of Sorcery Points equal to the spell's level. If you cast the spell using Sorcery Points, it requires no Verbal or Somatic components, and it requires no Material components unless they are consumed by the spell or have a cost specified in it.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 146</text>
        <subclass>Aberrant Sorcery</subclass>
        <trigger text="when_you_cast_any_level_1+_spell_from_your_Psionic_Spells_feature"/>
        <alternative_casting_method>
          <cost type="SorceryPoints" value_formula="spells_level"/>
          <modifies_spell_components no_verbal="true" no_somatic="true" no_material_unless_consumed_or_costly="true"/>
        </alternative_casting_method>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 6: Psychic Defenses (Aberrant Sorcery)</name>
        <text>You have Resistance to Psychic damage, and you have Advantage on saving throws to avoid or end the Charmed or Frightened condition.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 146</text>
        <subclass>Aberrant Sorcery</subclass>
        <effect type="Resistance" damage_types="Psychic"/>
        <effect type="Advantage" on="saving_throws_to_avoid_or_end_Charmed_or_Frightened_condition"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 14: Revelation In Flesh (Aberrant Sorcery)</name>
        <text>You can unleash the aberrant truth hidden within yourself. As a Bonus Action, you can spend 1 Sorcery Point or more to magically alter your body for 10 minutes. For each Sorcery Point you spend, you gain one of the following benefits of your choice, the effects of which last until the alteration ends.

Aquatic Adaptation. You gain a Swim Speed equal to twice your Speed, and you can breathe underwater. Gills grow from your neck or flare behind your ears, and your fingers become webbed or you grow wriggling cilia.

Glistening Flight. You gain a Fly Speed equal to your Speed, and you can hover. As you fly, your skin glistens with mucus or otherworldly light.

See the Invisible. You can see any Invisible creature within 60 feet of yourself that isn't behind Total Cover. Your eyes also turn black or become writhing sensory tendrils.

Wormlike Movement. Your body, along with any equipment you are wearing or carrying, becomes slimy and pliable. You can move through any space as narrow as 1 inch, and you can spend 5 feet of movement to escape from nonmagical restraints or the Grappled condition.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 146</text>
        <subclass>Aberrant Sorcery</subclass>
        <action type="BonusAction"/>
        <cost type="SorceryPoints" value_variable="1_or_more"/>
        <effect type="Transformation" name="AberrantAlteration" duration="10_minutes">
          <choice_of_benefits count_formula="SorceryPointsSpent">
            <option name="Aquatic Adaptation">
              <effect type="Speed" speed_type="Swim" value_formula="2*Speed"/>
              <effect description="can_breathe_underwater_gills_grow_fingers_webbed_or_cilia_grow"/>
            </option>
            <option name="Glistening Flight">
              <effect type="Speed" speed_type="Fly" value_formula="Speed"/>
              <effect description="can_hover_skin_glistens_with_mucus_or_otherworldly_light"/>
            </option>
            <option name="See the Invisible">
              <effect type="Sense" name="SeeInvisible" range="60_feet" condition="not_behind_Total_Cover"/>
              <effect description="eyes_turn_black_or_become_writhing_sensory_tendrils"/>
            </option>
            <option name="Wormlike Movement">
              <effect description="body_and_equipment_become_slimy_and_pliable_can_move_through_any_space_as_narrow_as_1_inch"/>
              <effect description="can_spend_5_feet_of_movement_to_escape_from_nonmagical_restraints_or_Grappled_condition"/>
            </option>
          </choice_of_benefits>
        </effect>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 18: Warping Implosion (Aberrant Sorcery)</name>
        <text>You can unleash a space-warping anomaly. As a Magic action, you teleport to an unoccupied space you can see within 120 feet of yourself. Immediately after you disappear, each creature within 30 feet of the space you left must make a Strength saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, a creature takes 3d10 Force damage and is pulled straight toward the space you left, ending in an unoccupied space as close to your former space as possible. On a successful save, the creature takes half as much damage only.

Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a Long Rest unless you spend 5 Sorcery Points (no action required) to restore your use of it.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 146</text>
        <subclass>Aberrant Sorcery</subclass>
        <action type="MagicAction">
          <effect type="Teleport" target="self" range="up_to_120_feet" destination="unoccupied_space_you_can_see"/>
          <effect description="immediately_after_you_disappear_each_creature_within_30_feet_of_space_you_left_must_make_STR_save" save_dc="spell_save_DC">
            <on_failed_save>
              <effect type="Damage" damage_type="Force" value="3d10"/>
              <effect type="Movement" target="creature" direction="pulled_straight_toward_space_you_left_ending_in_unoccupied_space_as_close_as_possible"/>
            </on_failed_save>
            <on_successful_save type="Damage" damage_type="Force" value="half_of_3d10"/>
          </effect>
        </action>
        <uses fixed="1"/>
        <recharge type="LR"/>
        <can_reuse_by_expending resource="SorceryPoints" value="5" action_type="NoAction"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Sorcerer Subclass: Clockwork Sorcery -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Sorcerer Subclass: Clockwork Sorcery</name>
        <text>Channel Cosmic Forces of Order

The cosmic force of order has suffused you with magic. That power arises from Mechanus or a realm like it- a plane of existence shaped entirely by clockwork efficiency. You or someone from your lineage might have become entangled in the machinations of modrons, the orderly beings who inhabit Mechanus. Perhaps your ancestor even took part in the Great Modron March. Whatever its origin within you, the power of order can seem strange to others, but for you, it's part of a vast and glorious system.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 146</text>
        <subclass>Clockwork Sorcery</subclass>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Clockwork Spells (Clockwork Sorcery)</name>
        <text>When you reach a Sorcerer level specified in the Clockwork Spells table, you thereafter always have the listed spells prepared.

Clockwork Spells:
Sorcerer Level | Spells
3 | Aid, Alarm, Lesser Restoration, Protection from Evil and Good
5 | Dispel Magic, Protection from Energy
7 | Freedom of Movement, Summon Construct
9 | Greater Restoration, Wall of Force

In addition, consult the Manifestations of Order table and choose or randomly determine a way your connection to order manifests while you are casting any of your Sorcerer spells.

Manifestations of Order:
1d6 | Manifestation
1 | Spectral cogwheels hover behind you.
2 | The hands of a clock spin in your eyes.
3 | Your skin glows with a brassy sheen.
4 | Floating equations and geometric objects overlay your body.
5 | Your Spellcasting Focus temporarily takes the form of a Tiny clockwork mechanism.
6 | The ticking of gears or ringing of a clock can be heard by you and those affected by your magic.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 146</text>
        <subclass>Clockwork Sorcery</subclass>
        <inline_table name="Clockwork Spells">
          <header>
            <col label="Sorcerer Level"/>
            <col label="Spells"/>
          </header>
          <row>
            <cell value="3"/>
            <cell value="Aid, Alarm, Lesser Restoration, Protection from Evil and Good"/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell value="5"/>
            <cell value="Dispel Magic, Protection from Energy"/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell value="7"/>
            <cell value="Freedom of Movement, Summon Construct"/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell value="9"/>
            <cell value="Greater Restoration, Wall of Force"/>
          </row>
        </inline_table>
        <choice name="ManifestationOfOrder" from_table="ManifestationsOfOrderTable" random_roll="1d6" description="manifests_while_casting_Sorcerer_spells"/>
        <inline_table name="Manifestations of Order Table">
          <header><col label="d6"/><col label="Manifestation"/></header>
          <row><cell value="1"/><cell value="Spectral cogwheels hover behind you."/></row>
          <row><cell value="2"/><cell value="The hands of a clock spin in your eyes."/></row>
          <row><cell value="3"/><cell value="Your skin glows with a brassy sheen."/></row>
          <row><cell value="4"/><cell value="Floating equations and geometric objects overlay your body."/></row>
          <row><cell value="5"/><cell value="Your Spellcasting Focus temporarily takes the form of a Tiny clockwork mechanism."/></row>
          <row><cell value="6"/><cell value="The ticking of gears or ringing of a clock can be heard by you and those affected by your magic."/></row>
        </inline_table>
        <roll description="Manifestation">1d6</roll>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Restore Balance (Clockwork Sorcery)</name>
        <text>Your connection to the plane of absolute order allows you to equalize chaotic moments. When a creature you can see within 60 feet of yourself is about to roll a d20 with Advantage or Disadvantage, you can take a Reaction to prevent the roll from being affected by Advantage and Disadvantage.
	You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a Long Rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 146</text>
        <subclass>Clockwork Sorcery</subclass>
        <action type="Reaction"/>
        <trigger text="when_a_creature_you_can_see_within_60_feet_is_about_to_roll_a_d20_with_Advantage_or_Disadvantage"/>
        <effect description="prevent_the_roll_from_being_affected_by_Advantage_and_Disadvantage"/>
        <uses attribute="CHA" min="1"/>
        <recharge type="LR"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 6: Bastion of Law (Clockwork Sorcery)</name>
        <text>You can tap into the grand equation of existence to imbue a creature with a shimmering shield of order. As a Magic action, you can expend 1 to 5 Sorcery Points to create a magical ward around yourself or another creature you can see within 30 feet of yourself. The ward is represented by a number of d8s equal to the number of Sorcery Points spent to create it. When the warded creature takes damage, it can expend a number of those dice, roll them, and reduce the damage taken by the total rolled on those dice.
	The ward lasts until you finish a Long Rest or until you use this feature again.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 147</text>
        <subclass>Clockwork Sorcery</subclass>
        <action type="MagicAction"/>
        <cost type="SorceryPoints" value_range="1-5"/>
        <target_choice>
          <option_target>self</option_target>
          <option_target description="another_creature_you_can_see_within_30_feet"/>
        </target_choice>
        <effect type="CreateWard" name="MagicalWard" dice_count_formula="SorceryPointsSpent" die_type="d8" duration="until_LR_or_use_this_feature_again">
          <ward_mechanic>
            <trigger text="when_warded_creature_takes_damage"/>
            <effect description="can_expend_a_number_of_those_dice_roll_them_and_reduce_damage_taken_by_total_rolled"/>
          </ward_mechanic>
        </effect>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 14: Trance of Order (Clockwork Sorcery)</name>
        <text>You gain the ability to align your consciousness with the endless calculations of Mechanus. As a Bonus Action, you can enter this state for 1 minute. For the duration, attack rolls against you can't benefit from Advantage, and whenever you make a D20 Test, you can treat a roll of 9 or lower on the d20 as a 10.
	Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a Long Rest unless you spend 5 Sorcery Points (no action required) to restore your use of it.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 147</text>
        <subclass>Clockwork Sorcery</subclass>
        <action type="BonusAction"/>
        <effect type="Buff" name="TranceOfOrderState" duration="1_minute">
          <benefits>
            <benefit description="attack_rolls_against_you_cant_benefit_from_Advantage"/>
            <benefit description="whenever_you_make_a_D20_Test_you_can_treat_a_roll_of_9_or_lower_on_the_d20_as_a_10"/>
          </benefits>
        </effect>
        <uses fixed="1"/>
        <recharge type="LR"/>
        <can_reuse_by_expending resource="SorceryPoints" value="5" action_type="NoAction"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Trance of Order</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
        <subclass>Clockwork Sorcery</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 18: Clockwork Cavalcade (Clockwork Sorcery)</name>
        <text>You momentarily summon spirits of order to expunge disorder around you. As a Magic action, you summon the spirits in a 30-foot Cube originating from you. The spirits look like modrons or other Constructs of your choice. The spirits are intangible and invulnerable, and they create the effects below within the Cube before vanishing. Once you use this action, you can't use it again until you finish a Long Rest unless you spend 7 Sorcery Points (no action required) to restore your use of it.

Heal. The spirits restore up to 100 Hit Points, divided as you choose among any number of creatures of your choice in the Cube.

Repair. Any damaged objects entirely in the Cube are repaired instantly.

Dispel. Every spell of level 6 and lower ends on creatures and objects of your choice in the Cube.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 147</text>
        <subclass>Clockwork Sorcery</subclass>
        <action type="MagicAction"/>
        <effect type="SummonSpirits" name="SpiritsOfOrder" appearance="modrons_or_other_Constructs_of_your_choice" area="30_foot_Cube_originating_from_you" properties="intangible_invulnerable">
          <effects_in_cube>
            <effect_option name="Heal">
              <effect type="Heal" value_total="100" target_description="divided_as_you_choose_among_any_number_of_creatures_of_your_choice_in_the_Cube"/>
            </effect_option>
            <effect_option name="Repair">
              <effect description="any_damaged_objects_entirely_in_the_Cube_are_repaired_instantly"/>
            </effect_option>
            <effect_option name="Dispel">
              <effect type="DispelMagic" max_spell_level="6" target_description="creatures_and_objects_of_your_choice_in_the_Cube"/>
            </effect_option>
          </effects_in_cube>
        </effect>
        <uses fixed="1"/>
        <recharge type="LR"/>
        <can_reuse_by_expending resource="SorceryPoints" value="7" action_type="NoAction"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Clockwork Cavalcade</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
        <subclass>Clockwork Sorcery</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Sorcerer Subclass: Draconic Sorcery -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Sorcerer Subclass: Draconic Sorcery</name>
        <text>Breathe the Magic of Dragons

Your innate magic comes from the gift of a dragon. Perhaps an ancient dragon facing death bequeathed some of its magical power to you or your ancestor. You might have absorbed magic from a site infused with dragons' power. Or perhaps you handled a treasure taken from a dragon's hoard that was steeped in draconic power. Or you might have a dragon for an ancestor.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 148</text>
        <subclass>Draconic Sorcery</subclass>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Draconic Resilience (Draconic Sorcery)</name>
        <text>The magic in your body manifests physical traits of your draconic gift. Your Hit Point maximum increases by 3, and it increases by 1 whenever you gain another Sorcerer level.
	Parts of you are also covered by dragon-like scales. While you aren't wearing armor, your base Armor Class equals 10 plus your Dexterity and Charisma modifiers.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 148</text>
        <subclass>Draconic Sorcery</subclass>
        <effect type="HitPointMaximumIncrease" value_initial="3" value_per_level_after_this="1"/>
        <modifier category="bonus">hp +3</modifier> <!-- Simple representation -->
        <modifies_rule rule_name="ArmorClassCalculation" condition="while_not_wearing_armor">
          <new_formula>10+DEX_modifier+CHA_modifier</new_formula>
        </modifies_rule>
        <special>Unarmored Defense: Charisma</special>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Draconic Spells (Draconic Sorcery)</name>
        <text>When you reach a Sorcerer level specified in the Draconic Spells table, you thereafter always have the listed spells prepared.

Draconic Spells:
Sorcerer Level | Spells
3 | Alter Self, Chromatic Orb, Command, Dragon's Breath
5 | Fear, Fly
7 | Arcane Eye, Charm Monster
9 | Legend Lore, Summon Dragon

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 148</text>
        <subclass>Draconic Sorcery</subclass>
        <inline_table name="Draconic Spells">
          <header>
            <col label="Sorcerer Level"/>
            <col label="Spells"/>
          </header>
          <row>
            <cell value="3"/>
            <cell value="Alter Self, Chromatic Orb, Command, Dragon's Breath"/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell value="5"/>
            <cell value="Fear, Fly"/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell value="7"/>
            <cell value="Arcane Eye, Charm Monster"/>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell value="9"/>
            <cell value="Legend Lore, Summon Dragon"/>
          </row>
        </inline_table>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 6: Elemental Affinity (Draconic Sorcery)</name>
        <text>Your draconic magic has an affinity with a damage type associated with dragons. Choose one of those types: Acid, Cold, Fire, Lightning, or Poison.
	You have Resistance to that damage type, and when you cast a spell that deals damage of that type, you can add your Charisma modifier to one damage roll of that spell.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 148</text>
        <subclass>Draconic Sorcery</subclass>
        <choice name="ElementalAffinityDamageType" from_list="Acid,Cold,Fire,Lightning,Poison" count="1"/>
        <effect type="Resistance" damage_types="chosen_elemental_affinity_type"/>
        <trigger text="when_you_cast_a_spell_that_deals_damage_of_chosen_type"/>
        <effect type="DamageBonus" value_formula="CHA_modifier" on_roll_count="one"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 14: Dragon Wings (Draconic Sorcery)</name>
        <text>As a Bonus Action, you can cause draconic wings to appear on your back. The wings last for 1 hour or until you dismiss them (no action required). For the duration, you have a Fly Speed of 60 feet.
	Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a Long Rest unless you spend 3 Sorcery Points (no action required) to restore your use of it.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 148</text>
        <subclass>Draconic Sorcery</subclass>
        <action type="BonusAction"/>
        <effect description="cause_draconic_wings_to_appear_on_your_back" duration="1_hour_or_until_dismissed_no_action">
          <benefit type="Speed" speed_type="Fly" value="60_feet"/>
        </effect>
        <uses fixed="1"/>
        <recharge type="LR"/>
        <can_reuse_by_expending resource="SorceryPoints" value="3" action_type="NoAction"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Dragon Wings</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
        <subclass>Draconic Sorcery</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 18: Dragon Companion (Draconic Sorcery)</name>
        <text>You can cast Summon Dragon without a Material component. You can also cast it once without a spell slot, and you regain the ability to cast it in this way when you finish a Long Rest.
	Whenever you start casting the spell, you can modify it so that it doesn't require Concentration. If you do so, the spell's duration becomes 1 minute for that casting.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 149</text>
        <subclass>Draconic Sorcery</subclass>
        <modifies_spell spell_name="Summon Dragon">
          <can_cast_without_material_component="true"/>
          <option_to_modify_casting>
            <effect description="doesnt_require_Concentration_duration_becomes_1_minute"/>
          </option_to_modify_casting>
        </modifies_spell>
        <uses fixed="1" for_casting_spell="Summon Dragon" without_slot="true">
          <recharge type="LR"/>
        </uses>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Sorcerer Subclass: Wild Magic Sorcery -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Sorcerer Subclass: Wild Magic Sorcery</name>
        <text>Unleash Chaotic Magic

Your innate magic stems from the forces of chaos that underlie the order of creation. You or an ancestor might have endured exposure to raw magic, perhaps through a planar portal leading to Limbo or the Elemental Planes. Perhaps you were blessed by a fey being or marked by a demon. Or your magic could be a fluke with no apparent cause. Whatever its source, this magic churns within you, waiting for any outlet.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 149</text>
        <subclass>Wild Magic Sorcery</subclass>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Wild Magic Surge (Wild Magic Sorcery)</name>
        <text>Your spellcasting can unleash surges of untamed magic. Once per turn, you can roll 1d20 immediately after you cast a Sorcerer spell with a spell slot. If you roll a 20, roll on the Wild Magic Surge table to create a magical effect.
	If the magical effect is a spell, it is too wild to be affected by your Metamagic.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 149</text>
        <subclass>Wild Magic Sorcery</subclass>
        <uses fixed="1" per_turn="true"/>
        <trigger text="immediately_after_you_cast_a_Sorcerer_spell_with_a_spell_slot"/>
        <effect description="can_roll_1d20_If_you_roll_a_20_roll_on_Wild_Magic_Surge_table_to_create_magical_effect"/>
        <restriction text="if_magical_effect_is_a_spell_it_is_too_wild_to_be_affected_by_your_Metamagic"/>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Tides of Chaos (Wild Magic Sorcery)</name>
        <text>You can manipulate chaos itself to give yourself Advantage on one 020 Test before you roll the d20. Once you do so, you must cast a Sorcerer spell with a spell slot or finish a Long Rest before you can use this feature again.
	If you do cast a Sorcerer spell with a spell slot before you finish a Long Rest, you automatically roll on the Wild Magic Surge table.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 149</text>
        <subclass>Wild Magic Sorcery</subclass>
        <effect type="Advantage" on="one_D20_Test_before_you_roll_d20"/>
        <uses fixed="1"/>
        <recharge type="Special" description="must_cast_a_Sorcerer_spell_with_a_spell_slot_or_finish_a_Long_Rest"/>
        <trigger text="if_you_cast_a_Sorcerer_spell_with_a_spell_slot_before_you_finish_a_Long_Rest_after_using_Tides_of_Chaos">
          <effect description="automatically_roll_on_the_Wild_Magic_Surge_table"/>
        </trigger>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 6: Bend Luck (Wild Magic Sorcery)</name>
        <text>You have the ability to twist fate using your wild magic. Immediately after another creature you can see rolls the d20 for a D20 Test, you can take a Reaction and spend 1 Sorcery Point to roll 1d4 and apply t he number rolled as a bonus or penalty (your choice) to the d20 roll.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 149</text>
        <subclass>Wild Magic Sorcery</subclass>
        <action type="Reaction"/>
        <trigger text="immediately_after_another_creature_you_can_see_rolls_the_d20_for_a_D20_Test"/>
        <cost resource="SorceryPoints" value="1"/>
        <effect description="roll_1d4_and_apply_the_number_rolled_as_a_bonus_or_penalty_your_choice_to_the_d20_roll"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 14: Controlled Chaos (Wild Magic Sorcery)</name>
        <text>You gain a modicum of control over the surges of your wild magic. Whenever you roll on the Wild Magic Surge table, you can roll twice and use either number.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 149</text>
        <subclass>Wild Magic Sorcery</subclass>
        <enhances_feature feature_name="Level 3: Wild Magic Surge (Wild Magic Sorcery)">
          <trigger text="whenever_you_roll_on_the_Wild_Magic_Surge_table"/>
          <effect description="can_roll_twice_and_use_either_number"/>
        </enhances_feature>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 18: Tamed Surge (Wild Magic Sorcery)</name>
        <text>Immediately after you cast a Sorcerer spell with a spell slot, you can create an effect of your choice from the Wild Magic Surge table instead of rolling on that table. You can choose any effect in the table except for the final row, and if the chosen effect involves a roll, you must make it.
	Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a Long Rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 150</text>
        <subclass>Wild Magic Sorcery</subclass>
        <trigger text="immediately_after_you_cast_a_Sorcerer_spell_with_a_spell_slot"/>
        <effect description="can_create_an_effect_of_your_choice_from_the_Wild_Magic_Surge_table_instead_of_rolling_cannot_choose_final_row_if_chosen_effect_involves_roll_must_make_it"/>
        <uses fixed="1"/>
        <recharge type="LR"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Tamed Surge</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
        <subclass>Wild Magic Sorcery</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
