<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
  <class>
    <name>Monk [2024]</name>
    <hd>8</hd>
    <proficiency>Strength, Dexterity, Acrobatics, Athletics, History, Insight, Religion, Stealth</proficiency>
    <numSkills>2</numSkills>
    <armor>none</armor>
    <weapons>Simple weapons and Martial weapons that have the Light property</weapons>
    <tools>any one type of artisan's tools or any one musical instrument of your choice</tools>
    <slotsReset>L</slotsReset> <!-- This seems to be a remnant, Monks don't use spell slots in the traditional sense -->
    <trait>
      <name>Monk</name>
      <text>Monks use rigorous combat training and mental discipline to align themselves with the multiverse and focus their internal reservoirs of power. Different Monks conceptualize this power in various ways: as breath, energy, life force, essence, or self, for example. Whether channeled as a striking display of martial prowess or as a subtler manifestation of defense and speed, this power infuses all that a Monk does.
	Monks focus their internal power to create extraordinary, even supernatural, effects. They channel uncanny speed and strength into their attacks, with or without the use of weapons. In a Monk's hands, even the most basic weapons can become sophisticated implements of combat mastery.
	Many Monks find that a structured life of ascetic withdrawal helps them cultivate the physical and mental focus they need to harness their power. Other Monks believe that immersing themselves in the vibrant confusion of life helps to fuel their determination and discipline.
	Monks generally view adventures as tests of their physical and mental development. They are driven by a desire to accomplish a greater mission than merely slaying monsters and plundering treasure; they strive to turn themselves into living weapons.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 101</text>
    </trait>
    <autolevel level="1">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Becoming A Monk As A Level 1 Character</name>
        <text>As a 1st-level Monk, you begin play with 8 + your Constitution modifier hit points.

Core Monk Traits
Primary Ability: Dexterity and Wisdom
Hit Point Die: D8 per Monk level
Saving Throw Proficiencies: Strength and Dexterity
Skill Proficiencies: Choose 2: Acrobatics, Athletics, History, Insight, Religion, or Stealth
Weapon Proficiencies: Simple weapons and Martial weapons that have the Light property
Tool Proficiencies: Choose one type of Artisan's Tools or Musical Instrument (see chapter 6)
Armor Training: None
Starting Equipment: Choose A or B: (A) Spear, 5 Daggers, Artisan's Tools or Musical Instrument chosen for the tool proficiency above, Explorer's Pack, and 11 GP; or (B) 50 GP

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 101</text>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Becoming A Monk As A Multiclass Character</name>
        <text>Core Monk Traits
Primary Ability: Dexterity and Wisdom
Hit Point Die: D8 per Monk level

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 101</text>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Level 1: Martial Arts</name>
        <text>Your practice of martial arts gives you mastery of combat styles that use your Unarmed Strike and Monk weapons, which are the following:

	• Simple Melee weapons
	• Martial Melee weapons that have the Light property

You gain the following benefits while you are unarmed or wielding only Monk weapons and you aren't wearing armor or wielding a Shield.
<equipment_condition_sets logic="OR">
  <condition_set armor_type="none" shield_handling="not_allowed" weapon_handling_unarmed_only="true"/>
  <condition_set armor_type="none" shield_handling="not_allowed" weapon_category="SimpleMeleeOrMartialMeleeWithLightProperty"/>
</equipment_condition_sets>

Bonus Unarmed Strike. You can make an Unarmed Strike as a Bonus Action.

Martial Arts Die. You can roll 1d6 in place of the normal damage of your Unarmed Strike or Monk weapons. This die changes as you gain Monk levels. as shown in the Martial Arts column of the Monk Features table. (d8 at level 5, d10 at level 11, d12 at level 17)

Dexterous Attacks. You can use your Dexterity modifier instead of your Strength modifier for the attack and damage rolls of your Unarmed Strikes and Monk weapons. In addition, when you use the Grapple or Shove option of your Unarmed Strike, you can use your Dexterity modifier instead of your Strength modifier to determine the save DC.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 101</text>
        <defines_category name="MonkWeapon" description="Simple Melee weapons AND Martial Melee weapons that have the Light property"/>
        <benefits>
          <benefit name="Bonus Unarmed Strike">
            <action type="BonusAction">
              <effect description="make_an_Unarmed_Strike"/>
            </action>
          </benefit>
          <benefit name="Martial Arts Die">
            <resource name="MartialArtsDie" die_scaling_table="MonkFeaturesTable_MartialArtsColumn" initial_die="1d6">
              <scaling level="5" die="1d8"/>
              <scaling level="11" die="1d10"/>
              <scaling level="17" die="1d12"/>
            </resource>
            <effect description="can_roll_MartialArtsDie_in_place_of_normal_damage_of_your_Unarmed_Strike_or_Monk_weapons"/>
          </benefit>
          <benefit name="Dexterous Attacks">
            <modifies_rule rule_name="UnarmedStrikeAndMonkWeaponAttackAndDamageRolls" new_basis="Dexterity_modifier_instead_of_Strength"/>
            <modifies_rule rule_name="UnarmedStrikeGrappleOrShoveSaveDC" new_basis="Dexterity_modifier_instead_of_Strength"/>
          </benefit>
        </benefits>
        <roll description="Unarmed Strike" level="1">1d6</roll>
        <roll description="Unarmed Strike" level="5">1d8</roll>
        <roll description="Unarmed Strike" level="11">1d10</roll>
        <roll description="Unarmed Strike" level="17">1d12</roll>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Level 1: Unarmored Defense</name>
        <text>While you aren't wearing armor or wielding a Shield, your base Armor Class equals 10 plus your Dexterity and Wisdom modifiers.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 101</text>
        <special>Unarmored Defense: Wisdom</special>
        <equipment_requirements armor="none" shield="false"/>
        <modifies_rule rule_name="ArmorClassCalculation">
          <new_formula>10 + DEX_modifier + WIS_modifier</new_formula>
        </modifies_rule>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 2: Monk's Focus</name> <!-- Changed from "Focus Points" to "Monk's Focus" to match text header, resource is Focus Points -->
        <text>Your focus and martial training allow you to harness a well of extraordinary energy within yourself. This energy is represented by Focus Points. Your Monk level determines the number of points you have, as shown in the Focus Points column of the Monk Features table.
	You can expend these points to enhance or fuel certain Monk features. You start knowing three such features: Flurry of Blows, Patient Defense, and Step of the Wind, each of which is detailed below.
	When you expend a Focus Point, it is unavailable until you finish a Short or Long Rest, at the end of which you regain all your expended points.
	Some features that use Focus Points require your target to make a saving throw. The save DC equals 8 plus your Wisdom modifier and Proficiency Bonus.

Flurry of Blows. You can expend 1 Focus Point to make two Unarmed Strikes as a Bonus Action.

Patient Defense. You can take the Disengage action as a Bonus Action. Alternatively, you can expend 1 Focus Point to take both the Disengage and the Dodge actions as a Bonus Action.

Step of the Wind. You can take the Dash action as a Bonus Action. Alternatively, you can expend 1 Focus Point to take both the Disengage and Dash actions as a Bonus Action, and your jump distance is doubled for the turn.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 101</text>
        <resource name="FocusPoints" scaling_table="MonkFeaturesTable_FocusPointsColumn">
          <recharge type="SR_or_LR" description="regain_all_expended_points"/>
        </resource>
        <focus_point_save_dc formula="8+WIS+PROF"/>

        <action_option name="Flurry of Blows" type="BonusAction">
            <description_text>Expend 1 Focus Point to make two Unarmed Strikes as a Bonus Action.</description_text>
            <cost resource="FocusPoint" value="1"/>
            <effect description="make_two_Unarmed_Strikes"/>
        </action_option>

        <action_option name="Patient Defense" type="BonusAction">
            <description_text>Take the Disengage action as a Bonus Action. Alternatively, expend 1 Focus Point to take both the Disengage and the Dodge actions as a Bonus Action.</description_text>
            <choice name="PatientDefenseChoice">
                <option name="Disengage (No Cost)">
                    <effect description="take_the_Disengage_action"/>
                </option>
                <option name="Disengage and Dodge (Costs 1 Focus Point)">
                    <cost resource="FocusPoint" value="1"/>
                    <effect description="take_both_the_Disengage_and_the_Dodge_actions"/>
                </option>
            </choice>
        </action_option>

        <action_option name="Step of the Wind" type="BonusAction">
            <description_text>Take the Dash action as a Bonus Action. Alternatively, expend 1 Focus Point to take both the Disengage and Dash actions as a Bonus Action, and your jump distance is doubled for the turn.</description_text>
            <choice name="StepOfTheWindChoice">
                <option name="Dash (No Cost)">
                    <effect description="take_the_Dash_action"/>
                </option>
                <option name="Disengage and Dash (Costs 1 Focus Point)">
                    <cost resource="FocusPoint" value="1"/>
                    <effect description="take_both_the_Disengage_and_Dash_actions_AND_your_jump_distance_is_doubled_for_the_turn"/>
                </option>
            </choice>
        </action_option>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Level 2: Unarmored Movement</name>
        <text>Your speed increases by 10 feet while you aren't wearing armor or wielding a Shield. This bonus increases when you reach certain Monk levels, as shown on the Monk Features table.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 102</text>
        <equipment_requirements armor="none" shield="false"/>
        <modifier category="bonus">speed +10</modifier> <!-- Base value -->
        <effect type="SpeedIncrease" value_scaling_table="MonkFeaturesTable_UnarmoredMovementColumn"/>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Level 2: Uncanny Metabolism</name>
        <text>When you roll Initiative, you can regain all expended Focus Points. When you do so, roll your Martial Arts die, and regain a number of Hit Points equal to your Monk level plus the number rolled.
	Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a Long Rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 102</text>
        <trigger text="when_you_roll_Initiative"/>
        <effect description="regain_all_expended_Focus_Points_AND_roll_your_Martial_Arts_die_regain_HP_equal_to_Monk_level_plus_number_rolled"/>
        <uses fixed="1"/>
        <recharge type="LR"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>2</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
      <counter>
        <name>Uncanny Metabolism</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 3: Deflect Attacks</name> <!-- Renamed from Deflect Missiles to match text -->
        <text>When an attack roll hits you and its damage includes Bludgeoning, Piercing, or Slashing damage, you can take a Reaction to reduce the attack's total damage against you. The reduction equals 1d10 plus your Dexterity modifier and Monk level.
	If you reduce the damage to 0, you can expend 1 Focus Point to redirect some of the attack's force. If you do so, choose a creature you can see within 5 feet of yourself if the attack was a melee attack or a creature you can see within 60 feet of yourself that isn't behind Total Cover if the attack was a ranged attack. That creature must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or take damage equal to two rolls of your Martial Arts die plus your Dexterity modifier. The damage is the same type dealt by the attack.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 102</text>
        <action type="Reaction"/>
        <trigger text="when_an_attack_roll_hits_you_and_its_damage_includes_Bludgeoning_Piercing_or_Slashing_damage"/>
        <effect type="DamageReduction" value_formula="1d10+DEX_modifier+MonkLevel"/>
        <on_condition condition="if_you_reduce_the_damage_to_0">
          <cost resource="FocusPoint" value="1"/>
          <effect description="redirect_some_of_the_attacks_force_choose_creature_you_can_see_within_5ft_melee_or_60ft_ranged_not_total_cover_target_must_succeed_DEX_save_or_take_damage_equal_to_2_MartialArtsDieRolls+DEX_modifier_damage_type_same_as_attack" save_dc="focus_point_save_dc"/>
        </on_condition>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Level 3: Monk Subclass</name>
        <text>You gain a Monk subclass of your choice. The Warrior of Mercy, Warrior of Shadow, Warrior of the Elements, and Warrior of the Open Hand subclasses are detailed after this class's description. A subclass is a specialization that grants you features at certain Monk levels. For the rest of your career, you gain each of your subclass's features that are of your Monk level or lower.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>3</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 4: Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5) or another feat of your choice for which you qualify. You gain this feature again at Monk levels 8, 12, and 16.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
        <asi_options>
          <option description="Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5)"/>
          <option description="Another feat of your choice for which you qualify"/>
        </asi_options>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Level 4: Slow Fall</name>
        <text>You can take a Reaction when you fall to reduce any damage you take from the fall by an amount equal to five times your Monk level.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
        <action type="Reaction"/>
        <trigger text="when_you_fall"/>
        <effect type="DamageReduction" source="fall_damage" value_formula="5*MonkLevel"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>4</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 5: Extra Attack</name>
        <text>You can attack twice instead of once whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
        <modifies_action action_name="Attack" new_attacks_allowed="2"/>
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Level 5: Stunning Strike</name>
        <text>Once per turn when you hit a creature with a Monk weapon or an Unarmed Strike, you can expend 1 Focus Point to attempt a stunning strike. The target must make a Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the target has the Stunned condition until the start of your next turn. On a successful save, the target's Speed is halved until the start of your next turn, and the next attack roll made against the target before then has Advantage.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
        <uses fixed="1" per_turn="true"/>
        <trigger text="when_you_hit_a_creature_with_a_Monk_weapon_or_an_Unarmed_Strike"/>
        <cost resource="FocusPoint" value="1"/>
        <effect description="target_must_make_a_Constitution_saving_throw" save_dc="focus_point_save_dc">
          <on_failed_save type="Condition" name="Stunned" duration="until_start_of_your_next_turn"/>
          <on_successful_save>
            <effect type="SpeedReduction" value_halved="true" duration="until_start_of_your_next_turn"/>
            <effect type="Advantage" on="next_attack_roll_made_against_the_target_before_then"/>
          </on_successful_save>
        </effect>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>5</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 6: Empowered Strikes</name>
        <text>Whenever you deal damage with your Unarmed Strike, it can deal your choice of Force damage or its normal damage type.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
        <trigger text="whenever_you_deal_damage_with_your_Unarmed_Strike"/>
        <effect description="it_can_deal_your_choice_of_Force_damage_or_its_normal_damage_type"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>6</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 7: Evasion</name>
        <text>When you're subjected to an effect that allows you to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, you instead take no damage if you succeed on the saving throw and only half damage if you fail.
	You don't benefit from this feature if you have the Incapacitated condition.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
        <trigger text="when_youre_subjected_to_an_effect_that_allows_you_to_make_a_Dexterity_saving_throw_to_take_only_half_damage"/>
        <modifies_effect original_success="half_damage" original_fail="half_damage" new_success="no_damage" new_fail="half_damage"/>
        <restriction text="dont_benefit_if_Incapacitated"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>7</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 8: Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5) or another feat of your choice for which you qualify. You gain this feature again at Monk levels 8, 12, and 16.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
        <asi_options>
          <option description="Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5)"/>
          <option description="Another feat of your choice for which you qualify"/>
        </asi_options>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>8</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 9: Acrobatic Movement</name>
        <text>While you aren't wearing armor or wielding a Shield, you gain the ability to move along vertical surfaces and across liquids on your turn without falling during the movement.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
        <equipment_requirements armor="none" shield="false"/>
        <effect description="gain_the_ability_to_move_along_vertical_surfaces_and_across_liquids_on_your_turn_without_falling_during_the_movement"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>9</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 10: Heightened Focus</name>
        <text>Your Flurry of Blows, Patient Defense, and Step of the Wind gain the following benefits.

Flurry of Blows. You can expend 1 Focus Point to use Flurry of Blows and make three Unarmed Strikes with it instead of two.

Patient Defense. When you expend a Focus Point to use Patient Defense, you gain a number of Temporary Hit Points equal to two rolls of your Martial Arts die.

Step of the Wind. When you expend a Focus Point to use Step of the Wind, you can choose a willing creature within 5 feet of yourself that is Large or smaller. You move the creature with you until the end of your turn. The creature's movement doesn't provoke Opportunity Attacks.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
        <enhancements>
          <enhances_ability ability_name="Flurry of Blows">
            <effect description="can_expend_1_Focus_Point_to_make_three_Unarmed_Strikes_instead_of_two"/>
          </enhances_ability>
          <enhances_ability ability_name="Patient Defense">
            <trigger text="when_you_expend_a_Focus_Point_to_use_Patient_Defense"/>
            <effect type="GainTemporaryHitPoints" value_formula="2*MartialArtsDieRoll"/>
          </enhances_ability>
          <enhances_ability ability_name="Step of the Wind">
            <trigger text="when_you_expend_a_Focus_Point_to_use_Step_of_the_Wind"/>
            <effect description="can_choose_a_willing_creature_within_5_feet_Large_or_smaller_You_move_the_creature_with_you_until_end_of_your_turn_Creatures_movement_doesnt_provoke_Opportunity_Attacks"/>
          </enhances_ability>
        </enhancements>
        <modifier category="bonus">speed +5</modifier> <!-- Unarmored Movement -->
      </feature>
      <feature>
        <name>Level 10: Self-Restoration</name>
        <text>Through sheer force of will, you can remove one of the following conditions from yourself at the end of each of your turns: Charmed, Frightened, or Poisoned.
	In addition, forgoing food and drink doesn't give you levels of Exhaustion.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
        <trigger text="at_the_end_of_each_of_your_turns"/>
        <effect description="can_remove_one_of_the_following_conditions_from_yourself_Charmed_Frightened_or_Poisoned"/>
        <modifies_rule rule_name="ExhaustionFromFoodAndDrink" status="immune"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>10</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>11</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 12: Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5) or another feat of your choice for which you qualify. You gain this feature again at Monk levels 8, 12, and 16.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
        <asi_options>
          <option description="Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5)"/>
          <option description="Another feat of your choice for which you qualify"/>
        </asi_options>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>12</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 13: Deflect Energy</name>
        <text>You can now use your Deflect Attacks feature against attacks that deal any damage type, not just Bludgeoning, Piercing, or Slashing.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
        <enhances_feature feature_name="Level 3: Deflect Attacks">
          <modifies_trigger new_damage_types_affected="any_damage_type"/>
        </enhances_feature>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>13</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 14: Disciplined Survivor</name>
        <text>Your physical and mental discipline grant you proficiency in all saving throws.
	Additionally, whenever you make a saving throw and fail, you can expend 1 Focus Point to reroll it. and you must use the new roll.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
        <grants_proficiency type="SavingThrow" name="Strength"/> <!-- Already has Str, Dex. Adding others. -->
        <grants_proficiency type="SavingThrow" name="Constitution"/>
        <grants_proficiency type="SavingThrow" name="Intelligence"/>
        <grants_proficiency type="SavingThrow" name="Wisdom"/>
        <grants_proficiency type="SavingThrow" name="Charisma"/>
        <proficiency>constitution, intelligence, wisdom, charisma</proficiency> <!-- Original, for compatibility -->
        <trigger text="whenever_you_make_a_saving_throw_and_fail"/>
        <cost resource="FocusPoint" value="1"/>
        <effect description="reroll_it_and_you_must_use_the_new_roll"/>
        <modifier category="bonus">speed +5</modifier> <!-- Unarmored Movement -->
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>14</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 15: Perfect Focus</name>
        <text>When you roll Initiative and don't use Uncanny Metabolism, you regain expended Focus Points until you have 4 if you have 3 or fewer.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
        <trigger text="when_you_roll_Initiative_and_dont_use_Uncanny_Metabolism"/>
        <condition text="if_you_have_3_or_fewer_Focus_Points"/>
        <effect description="regain_expended_Focus_Points_until_you_have_4"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>15</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16" scoreImprovement="YES">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 16: Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>You gain the Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5) or another feat of your choice for which you qualify. You gain this feature again at Monk levels 8, 12, and 16.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
        <asi_options>
          <option description="Ability Score Improvement feat (see chapter 5)"/>
          <option description="Another feat of your choice for which you qualify"/>
        </asi_options>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>16</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>17</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 18: Superior Defense</name>
        <text>At the start of your turn, you can expend 3 Focus Points to bolster yourself against harm for 1 minute or until you have the Incapacitated condition. During that time, you have Resistance to all damage except Force damage.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
        <trigger text="at_the_start_of_your_turn"/>
        <cost resource="FocusPoint" value="3"/>
        <effect type="Resistance" damage_types="all_except_Force" duration="1_minute_or_until_Incapacitated"/>
        <modifier category="bonus">speed +5</modifier> <!-- Unarmored Movement -->
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>18</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 19: Epic Boon</name>
        <text>You gain an Epic Boon feat (see chapter 5) or an· other feat of your choice for which you qualify. Boon of Irresistible Offense is recommended.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>19</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
      <feature>
        <name>Level 20: Body And Mind</name>
        <text>You have developed your body and mind to new heights. Your Dexterity and Wisdom scores increase by 4, to a maximum of 25.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 103</text>
        <modifier category="ability score">dexterity +4</modifier>
        <modifier category="ability score">wisdom +4</modifier>
        <effect type="AbilityScoreIncrease" ability="Dexterity" value="4" maximum="25"/>
        <effect type="AbilityScoreIncrease" ability="Wisdom" value="4" maximum="25"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Focus Points</name>
        <value>20</value>
        <reset>S</reset>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Monk Subclass: Warrior of Mercy -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Monk Subclass: Warrior of Mercy</name>
        <text>Manipulate Forces of Life and Death

Warriors of Mercy manipulate the life force of others. These Monks are wandering physicians, but they bring a swift end to their enemies. They often wear masks, presenting themselves as faceless bringers of life and death.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 104</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of Mercy</subclass>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Hand of Harm (Warrior of Mercy)</name>
        <text>Once per turn when you hit a creature with an Unarmed Strike and deal damage, you can expend 1 Focus Point to deal extra Necrotic damage equal to one roll of your Martial Arts die plus your Wisdom modifier.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 104</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of Mercy</subclass>
        <uses fixed="1" per_turn="true"/>
        <trigger text="when_you_hit_a_creature_with_an_Unarmed_Strike_and_deal_damage"/>
        <cost resource="FocusPoint" value="1"/>
        <effect type="ExtraDamage" damage_type="Necrotic" value_formula="MartialArtsDieRoll+WIS_modifier"/>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Hand of Healing (Warrior of Mercy)</name>
        <text>As a Magic action, you can expend 1 Focus Point to touch a creature and restore a number of Hit Points equal to a roll of your Martial Arts die plus your Wisdom modifier.
	When you use your Flurry of Blows, you can replace one of the Unarmed Strikes with a use of this feature without expending a Focus Point for the healing.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 104</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of Mercy</subclass>
        <action type="MagicAction">
          <cost resource="FocusPoint" value="1"/>
          <target description="a_creature_you_touch"/>
          <effect type="Heal" value_formula="MartialArtsDieRoll+WIS_modifier"/>
        </action>
        <enhances_ability ability_name="Flurry of Blows">
          <effect description="can_replace_one_of_the_Unarmed_Strikes_with_a_use_of_Hand_of_Healing_Magic_Action_without_expending_a_Focus_Point_for_the_healing"/>
        </enhances_ability>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Implements of Mercy (Warrior of Mercy)</name>
        <text>You gain proficiency in the Insight and Medicine skills and proficiency with the Herbalism Kit.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 104</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of Mercy</subclass>
        <grants_proficiency type="Skill" name="Insight"/>
        <grants_proficiency type="Skill" name="Medicine"/>
        <grants_proficiency type="Tool" name="Herbalism Kit"/>
        <proficiency>Insight, Medicine</proficiency> <!-- Original -->
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 6: Physician's Touch (Warrior of Mercy)</name>
        <text>Your Hand of Harm and Hand of Healing improve, as detailed below.

Hand of Harm. When you use Hand of Harm on a creature, you can also give that creature the Poisoned condition until the end of your next turn.

Hand of Healing. When you use Hand of Healing. you can also end one of the following conditions on the creature you heal: Blinded, Deafened, Paralyzed, Poisoned, or Stunned.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 104</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of Mercy</subclass>
        <enhancements>
          <enhances_feature feature_name="Level 3: Hand of Harm (Warrior of Mercy)">
            <trigger text="when_you_use_Hand_of_Harm_on_a_creature"/>
            <effect type="Condition" name="Poisoned" target="that_creature" duration="until_end_of_your_next_turn"/>
          </enhances_feature>
          <enhances_feature feature_name="Level 3: Hand of Healing (Warrior of Mercy)">
            <trigger text="when_you_use_Hand_of_Healing"/>
            <effect description="can_also_end_one_of_the_following_conditions_on_the_creature_you_heal_Blinded_Deafened_Paralyzed_Poisoned_or_Stunned"/>
          </enhances_feature>
        </enhancements>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 11 : Flurry of Healing And Harm (Warrior of Mercy)</name>
        <text>When you use Flurry of Blows, you can replace each of the Unarmed Strikes with a use of Hand of Healing without expending Focus Points for the healing.
	In addition, when you make an Unarmed Strike with Flurry of Blows and deal damage, you can use Hand of Harm with that strike without expending a Focus Point for Hand of Harm. You can s t ill use Hand of Harm only once per turn.
	You can use these benefits a total number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once). You regain all expended uses when you finish a Long Rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 104</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of Mercy</subclass>
        <uses attribute="WIS" min="1"/>
        <recharge type="LR"/>
        <enhancements>
          <enhances_ability ability_name="Flurry of Blows">
            <effect description="can_replace_each_of_the_Unarmed_Strikes_with_a_use_of_Hand_of_Healing_without_expending_Focus_Points_for_the_healing"/>
            <trigger text="when_you_make_an_Unarmed_Strike_with_Flurry_of_Blows_and_deal_damage"/>
            <effect description="can_use_Hand_of_Harm_with_that_strike_without_expending_a_Focus_Point_for_Hand_of_Harm_still_only_once_per_turn"/>
          </enhances_ability>
        </enhancements>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 17: Hand of Ultimate Mercy (Warrior of Mercy)</name>
        <text>Your mastery of life energy opens the door to the ultimate mercy. As a Magic action, you can touch the corpse of a creature that died within the past 24 hours and expend 5 Focus Points. The creature then returns to life with a number of Hit Points equal to 4d10 plus your Wisdom modifier. If the creature died with any of the following conditions, the creature revives with the conditions removed: Blinded, Deafened, Paralyzed, Poisoned, and Stunned.
	Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a Long Rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 105</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of Mercy</subclass>
        <action type="MagicAction"/>
        <target description="corpse_of_a_creature_that_died_within_the_past_24_hours"/>
        <cost resource="FocusPoint" value="5"/>
        <effect type="Revive" hp_formula="4d10+WIS_modifier"/>
        <effect description="if_creature_died_with_Blinded_Deafened_Paralyzed_Poisoned_or_Stunned_it_revives_with_conditions_removed"/>
        <uses fixed="1"/>
        <recharge type="LR"/>
      </feature>
      <counter>
        <name>Hand of Ultimate Mercy</name>
        <value>1</value>
        <reset>L</reset>
        <subclass>Warrior of Mercy</subclass>
      </counter>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Monk Subclass: Warrior of Shadow -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Monk Subclass: Warrior of Shadow</name>
        <text>Harness Shadow Power for Stealth and Subterfuge

Warriors of Shadow practice stealth and subterfuge, harnessing the power of the Shadowfell. They are at home in darkness, able to draw gloom around themselves to hide, leap from shadow to shadow, and take on a wraithlike form.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 105</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of Shadow</subclass>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Shadow Arts (Warrior of Shadow)</name>
        <text>You have learned to draw on the power of the Shadowfell, gaining the following benefits.

Darkness. You can expend 1 Focus Point to cast the Darkness spell without spell components. You can see within the spell's area when you cast it with this feature. While the spell persists, you can move its area of Darkness to a space within 60 feet of yourself at the start of each of your turns.

Darkvision. You gain Darkvision with a range of 60 fee t. If you already have Dark vision, its range increases by 60 feet.

Shadowy Figments. You know the Minor Illusion spell. Wisdom is your spellcasting ability for it.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 105</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of Shadow</subclass>
        <benefits>
          <benefit name="Darkness">
            <cost resource="FocusPoint" value="1"/>
            <effect description="cast_Darkness_spell_without_spell_components"/>
            <modifies_spell spell_name="Darkness" condition="when_cast_with_this_feature">
              <effect description="you_can_see_within_the_spells_area"/>
              <trigger text="while_the_spell_persists_at_the_start_of_each_of_your_turns"/>
              <effect description="can_move_its_area_of_Darkness_to_a_space_within_60_feet_of_yourself"/>
            </modifies_spell>
          </benefit>
          <benefit name="Darkvision">
            <effect type="Darkvision" range="60_feet"/>
            <enhancement condition="if_already_have_Darkvision" effect="its_range_increases_by_60_feet"/>
          </benefit>
          <benefit name="Shadowy Figments">
            <grants_spell_learning spell_name="Minor Illusion" ability="WIS"/>
          </benefit>
        </benefits>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 6 : Shadow Step (Warrior of Shadow)</name>
        <text>While entirely within Dim Light or Darkness, you can use a Bonus Action to teleport up to 60 feet to an unoccupied space you can see that is also in Dim Light or Darkness. You then have Advantage on the next me lee attack you make before the end of the current turn.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 105</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of Shadow</subclass>
        <condition text="while_entirely_within_Dim_Light_or_Darkness"/>
        <action type="BonusAction"/>
        <effect type="Teleport" target="self" range="up_to_60_feet" destination="unoccupied_space_you_can_see_that_is_also_in_Dim_Light_or_Darkness"/>
        <effect type="Advantage" on="next_melee_attack_you_make_before_end_of_current_turn"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 11: Improved Shadow Step (Warrior of Shadow)</name>
        <text>You can draw on your Shadowfell connection to empower your teleportation. When you use your Shadow Step, you can expend 1 Focus Point to remove the requirement that you must start and end in Dim Light or Darkness for that use of the feature. As part of this Bonus Action, you can make an Unarmed Strike immediately after you teleport.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 105</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of Shadow</subclass>
        <enhances_feature feature_name="Level 6 : Shadow Step (Warrior of Shadow)">
          <trigger text="when_you_use_your_Shadow_Step"/>
          <cost resource="FocusPoint" value="1"/>
          <effect description="remove_the_requirement_that_you_must_start_and_end_in_Dim_Light_or_Darkness_for_that_use"/>
          <effect description="as_part_of_this_Bonus_Action_can_make_an_Unarmed_Strike_immediately_after_you_teleport"/>
        </enhances_feature>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 17: Cloak of Shadows (Warrior of Shadow)</name>
        <text>As a Magic action while entirely within Dim Light or Darkness, you can expend 3 Focus Points to shroud yourself with shadows for 1 minute, until you have the Incapacitated condition, or until you end your turn in Bright Light. While shrouded by these shadows, you gain the following benefits.

Invisibility. You have the Invisible condition.

Partially Incorporeal. You can move through occupied spaces as if they were Difficult Terrain. If you end your turn in such a space, you are shunted to the last unoccupied space you were in.

Shadow Flurry. You can use your Flurry of Blows without expending any Focus Points.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 105</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of Shadow</subclass>
        <action type="MagicAction"/>
        <condition text="while_entirely_within_Dim_Light_or_Darkness"/>
        <cost resource="FocusPoint" value="3"/>
        <effect type="Transformation" name="ShroudOfShadows" duration="1_minute" ends_early_if="Incapacitated_condition_or_end_your_turn_in_Bright_Light">
          <benefits>
            <benefit name="Invisibility">
              <effect type="Condition" name="Invisible"/>
            </benefit>
            <benefit name="Partially Incorporeal">
              <effect description="can_move_through_occupied_spaces_as_if_they_were_Difficult_Terrain_If_you_end_your_turn_in_such_a_space_you_are_shunted_to_the_last_unoccupied_space_you_were_in"/>
            </benefit>
            <benefit name="Shadow Flurry">
              <modifies_ability ability_name="Flurry of Blows">
                <cost resource="FocusPoint" new_value="0"/>
              </modifies_ability>
            </benefit>
          </benefits>
        </effect>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Monk Subclass: Warrior of the Elements -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Monk Subclass: Warrior of the Elements</name>
        <text>Wield Strikes and Bursts of Elemental Power

Warriors of the Elements tap into the power of the Elemental Planes. Harnessing their supernatural focus, these Monks momentarily tame the energy of the Elemental Chaos to empower themselves in and out of battle.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 106</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of the Elements</subclass>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Elemental Attunement (Warrior of the Elements)</name>
        <text>At the start of your turn, you can expend l Focus Point to imbue yourself with elemental energy. The energy lasts for 10 minutes or until you have the Incapacitated condition. You gain the following benefits while this feature is active.

Reach. When you make an Unarmed Strike, your reach is 10 feet greater than normal, as elemental energy extends from you.

Elemental Strikes. Whenever you hit with your Unarmed Strike, you can cause it to deal your choice of Acid, Cold, Fire, Lightning, or Thunder damage rather than its normal damage type. When you deal one of these types with it, you can also force the target to make a Strength saving throw. On a failed save, you can move the target up to 10 feet toward or away from you, as elemental energy swirls around it.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 106</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of the Elements</subclass>
        <trigger text="at_the_start_of_your_turn"/>
        <cost resource="FocusPoint" value="1"/>
        <effect type="Buff" name="ElementalEnergyImbuement" duration="10_minutes" ends_early_if="Incapacitated_condition">
          <benefits_while_active>
            <benefit name="Reach">
              <trigger text="when_you_make_an_Unarmed_Strike"/>
              <effect type="ReachIncrease" value="10_feet_greater_than_normal"/>
            </benefit>
            <benefit name="Elemental Strikes">
              <trigger text="whenever_you_hit_with_your_Unarmed_Strike"/>
              <effect description="can_cause_it_to_deal_your_choice_of_Acid_Cold_Fire_Lightning_or_Thunder_damage_rather_than_its_normal_damage_type"/>
              <trigger text="when_you_deal_one_of_these_types_with_it"/>
              <effect description="can_also_force_the_target_to_make_a_Strength_saving_throw" save_dc="focus_point_save_dc">
                <on_failed_save>
                  <effect type="Movement" target="target" value="up_to_10_feet_toward_or_away_from_you"/>
                </on_failed_save>
              </effect>
            </benefit>
          </benefits_while_active>
        </effect>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Manipulate Elements (Warrior of the Elements)</name>
        <text>You know the Elementalism spell. Wisdom is your spellcasting ability for it.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 106</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of the Elements</subclass>
        <grants_spell_learning spell_name="Elementalism" ability="WIS"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 6: Elemental Burst (Warrior of the Elements)</name>
        <text>As a Magic action, you can expend 2 Focus Points to cause elemental energy to burst in a 20-foot-radius Sphere centered on a point within 120 feet of yourself. Choose a damage type: Acid, Cold, Fire, Lightning, or Thunder.
	Each creature in the Sphere must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes damage of the chosen type equal to three rolls of your Martial Arts die. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 106</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of the Elements</subclass>
        <action type="MagicAction"/>
        <cost resource="FocusPoint" value="2"/>
        <target_area type="Sphere" radius="20_feet" centered_on_point_within_range="120_feet"/>
        <damage_type_choice>Acid,Cold,Fire,Lightning,Thunder</damage_type_choice>
        <effect type="Damage" value_formula="3*MartialArtsDieRoll" save_type="DEX" save_dc="focus_point_save_dc" save_effect="half_damage" target_description="each_creature_in_the_Sphere"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 11: Stride of the Elements (Warrior of the Elements)</name>
        <text>While your Elemental Attunement is active, you also have a Fly Speed and a Swim Speed equal to your Speed.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 106</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of the Elements</subclass>
        <enhances_feature feature_name="Level 3: Elemental Attunement (Warrior of the Elements)">
          <benefit_while_active>
            <effect type="Speed" speed_type="Fly" value_formula="your_Speed"/>
            <effect type="Speed" speed_type="Swim" value_formula="your_Speed"/>
          </benefit_while_active>
        </enhances_feature>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 17: Elemental Epitome (Warrior of the Elements)</name>
        <text>While your Elemental Attunement is active, you also gain the following benefits.

Damage Resistance. You gain Resistance to one of the following damage types of your choice: Acid, Cold, Fire, Lightning, or Thunder. At the start of each of your turns, you can change this choice.

Destructive Stride. When you use your Step of the Wind, your Speed increases by 20 feet until the end of the turn. For that duration, any creature of your choice takes damage equal to one roll of your Martial Ar ts die when you enter a space within 5 feet of it. The damage type is your choice of Acid, Cold, Fire, Lightning, or Thunder. A creature can take this damage only once per turn.

Empowered Strikes. Once on each of your turns, you can deal extra damage to a target equal to one roll of your Martial Arts die when you hit it with an Unarmed Strike. The extra damage is the same type dealt by that strike.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 106</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of the Elements</subclass>
        <enhances_feature feature_name="Level 3: Elemental Attunement (Warrior of the Elements)">
          <benefits_while_active>
            <benefit name="Damage Resistance">
              <effect type="Resistance" damage_type_choice="Acid_Cold_Fire_Lightning_or_Thunder"/>
              <trigger text="at_the_start_of_each_of_your_turns">
                <effect description="can_change_this_choice"/>
              </trigger>
            </benefit>
            <benefit name="Destructive Stride">
              <enhances_ability ability_name="Step of the Wind">
                <effect type="SpeedIncrease" value="20_feet" duration="until_end_of_the_turn"/>
                <trigger text="for_that_duration_when_you_enter_a_space_within_5_feet_of_any_creature_of_your_choice"/>
                <effect type="Damage" value_formula="MartialArtsDieRoll" damage_type_choice="Acid_Cold_Fire_Lightning_or_Thunder" target="creature_entered_near"/>
                <restriction text="a_creature_can_take_this_damage_only_once_per_turn"/>
              </enhances_ability>
            </benefit>
            <benefit name="Empowered Strikes">
              <uses fixed="1" per_turn="true"/>
              <trigger text="when_you_hit_a_target_with_an_Unarmed_Strike"/>
              <effect type="ExtraDamage" value_formula="MartialArtsDieRoll" damage_type="same_as_strike"/>
            </benefit>
          </benefits_while_active>
        </enhances_feature>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <!-- Monk Subclass: Warrior of the Open Hand -->
    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Monk Subclass: Warrior of the Open Hand</name>
        <text>Master Unarmed Combat Techniques

Warriors of the Open Hand are masters of unarmed combat. They learn techniques to push and trip their opponents and manipulate their own energy to protect themselves from harm.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 107</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of the Open Hand</subclass>
      </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 3: Open Hand Technique (Warrior of the Open Hand)</name>
        <text>Whenever you hit a creature with an attack granted by your Flurry of Blows, you can impose one of the following effects on that target.

Addle. The target can't make Opportunity Attacks until the start of its next turn.

Push. The target must succeed on a Strength saving throw or be pushed up to 15 feet away from you.

Topple. The target must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or have the Prone condition.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 107</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of the Open Hand</subclass>
        <enhances_ability ability_name="Flurry of Blows">
          <trigger text="whenever_you_hit_a_creature_with_an_attack_granted_by_your_Flurry_of_Blows"/>
          <choice name="OpenHandTechniqueEffect" count="1">
            <option name="Addle">
              <effect description="target_cant_make_Opportunity_Attacks_until_start_of_its_next_turn"/>
            </option>
            <option name="Push">
              <effect description="target_must_succeed_on_a_Strength_saving_throw_or_be_pushed_up_to_15_feet_away_from_you" save_dc="focus_point_save_dc"/>
            </option>
            <option name="Topple">
              <effect description="target_must_succeed_on_a_Dexterity_saving_throw_or_have_the_Prone_condition" save_dc="focus_point_save_dc"/>
            </option>
          </choice>
        </enhances_ability>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 6: Wholeness of Body (Warrior of the Open Hand)</name>
        <text>You gain the ability to heal yourself. As a Bonus Action, you can roll your Martial Arts die. You regain a number of Hit Points equal to the number rolled plus your Wisdom modifier (minimum of 1 Hit Point regained).
	You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a Long Rest.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 107</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of the Open Hand</subclass>
        <action type="BonusAction"/>
        <effect type="Heal" target="self" value_formula="MartialArtsDieRoll+WIS_modifier" min_value="1"/>
        <uses attribute="WIS" min="1"/>
        <recharge type="LR"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 11: Fleet Step (Warrior of the Open Hand)</name>
        <text>When you take a Bonus Action other than Step of the Wind, you can also use Step of the Wind immediately after that Bonus Action.

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 107</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of the Open Hand</subclass>
        <trigger text="when_you_take_a_Bonus_Action_other_than_Step_of_the_Wind"/>
        <effect description="can_also_use_Step_of_the_Wind_immediately_after_that_Bonus_Action"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Level 17: Quivering Palm (Warrior of the Open Hand)</name>
        <text>You gain the ability to set up lethal vibrations in someone's body. When you hit a creature with an Unarmed Strike, you can expend 4 Focus Points to start these imperceptible vibrations, which last for a number of days equal to your Monk level. The vibrations are harmless unless you take an action to end them. Alternatively, when you take the Attack action on your turn, you can forgo one of the attacks to end the vibrations. To end them, you and the target must be on t he same plane of existence. When you end them, the target must make a Constitution saving throw, taking 10d12 Force damage on a failed save or half as much damage on a successful one.
	You can have only one creature under the effect of this feature at a time. You can end the vibrations harmlessly (no action required).

Source:	Player's Handbook 2024 p. 107</text>
        <subclass>Warrior of the Open Hand</subclass>
        <trigger text="when_you_hit_a_creature_with_an_Unarmed_Strike"/>
        <cost resource="FocusPoint" value="4"/>
        <effect type="ApplyDebuff" name="QuiveringPalmVibrations" duration_formula="MonkLevel_days" target="creature_hit">
          <description>vibrations_are_harmless_unless_you_take_an_action_to_end_them</description>
        </effect>
        <action_to_end_vibrations>
          <option name="DedicatedAction">
            <action type="Action"/>
          </option>
          <option name="ForgoAttack">
            <trigger text="when_you_take_the_Attack_action_on_your_turn"/>
            <cost description="forgo_one_of_the_attacks"/>
          </option>
        </action_to_end_vibrations>
        <condition_to_end_vibrations text="you_and_the_target_must_be_on_the_same_plane_of_existence"/>
        <effect_on_ending_vibrations description="target_must_make_a_Constitution_saving_throw" save_dc="focus_point_save_dc">
          <on_failed_save type="Damage" damage_type="Force" value="10d12"/>
          <on_successful_save type="Damage" damage_type="Force" value="half_of_10d12"/>
        </effect_on_ending_vibrations>
        <restriction text="can_have_only_one_creature_under_the_effect_of_this_feature_at_a_time_You_can_end_the_vibrations_harmlessly_no_action_required"/>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>
</compendium>
